Your source for Orthodox books, podcasts, videos, and more, we are ancient faith ministries.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will pray.
and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits,
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
angels, demons, and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat,
secular materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well? How do we perme-
every day life with spiritual presence.
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung host this live
Colin show focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey, thanks, voice of Steve.
Good evening, all you giant killers,
dragon slayers and election deniers.
You are listening to Laura Spirits' podcast,
my co-host.
the very Reverend, nearly double doctor, Stephen D. Young is with me straight from the swamp in Lafayette, Louisiana
and I'm Father Andrew Steamed with Damick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania, top the Eldritch Tower of Podcasting,
perched above a gateway to the underworld. And we are live. And if you are listening to us live, you can call us at 855-237-2346
and you can talk to us. We're going to get your calls in the second half of the show and Matzka Trudy, the tank, Richter. We'll be taking your calls.
I'll see you later.
So this episode is sponsored once again by the Orthodox Studies Institute at St. Constantine College
which exists to advance the study and application of Orthodox Christianity and faithfulness to
holy tradition by popular demand. OSI is bringing back our very own Father Stephen D'Young to teach a
live course on the book of Jubiles taking a deep dive into one of the most important texts in
Second Temple Judaism.
Course begins on January 7th, 2025.
Runs for four weeks.
you can learn more and you can register at orthodoxstudies.org slash LOS. And if you missed
Father Stevens' previous course on the book of Enoch, you can sign up for Jubilee's and also get
$25 off of Enoch by using that same link. So you can go to orthodoxstudies.org slash LOS to register
and see all of OSI's course offerings. And by the way, underway, right, is my course on Tolkien with
with OSI, and you can still register everybody, even if you weren't there to show up for the
first...
first class you're begging. Listen, I know. No. Hey, I advertised your thing for the last
two paragraphs. Okay. I'm just saying. This is like the Costco, of course, you buy
in bulk and you save. That's true. That's right. It sells here. So here in the United States
of America. We've been talking about election for some time now a lot.
You wouldn't think that such an important theological issue would be on every single TV
channel newspaper and YouTube show, but here we are.
So we figured we would weigh in on the most important election in our lifetimes, most
important election in the world.
So that said, sometimes we give a parental advisory at the beginning of episode, but this
time we're giving a Calvinist advisory.
So trigger warning.
Trigger warning.
Sorry.
Just in advance blanket.
Exactly.
It just, yeah.
If you are sensitive about, if you have Calvinist sensitivity, just turn off your radio right now.
Although I think, you know, given the general tenor of Calvinist, part of the reason we can
go so hard on them is that they can take it. I mean, that is their whole kind of gestalt. So yeah,
being a Calvinist and a snowflake kind of doesn't work. We have listeners by the way from
Czech Republic and Serbia, at least the night.
uh, in addition to our use an oh a Bavarian, an Alaskan, a North
Carolinian, a Kansan, a Californian. I mean, the list goes on and on.
South Carolinian. Wow. Apparently this guy from South Carolina claims that
South Carolina is the poor man's North Carolina. I mean, he said, Oh,
we've got an Australian as well. I mean, that's a lot of times on Hawaiian.
Of course, someone from the poor man's Ohio.
Texas. Wow. Hey everybody. Nice to see you all checking in there on the YouTube chat.
Who Northern Virginia? That's not real Virginia Sam. That's not real Virginia. I'm sorry.
Anyway. So what are we talking about Father Steven? We're talking about election.
Election. When God looks down at all of the evil people in the world and He chooses the lesser
evils and puts them in charge every two to four years.
Of all the kinds of
insects you could choose weevils weevils why weevils I don't know well they
wobble but they don't fall down nice that's a that is a 70s 80s reference right
there who I don't think they still sell those do they not that I've checked who
knows someone's good probably outlawed they're probably covered in lead paint yeah
exactly with you know spilling our childhood that's issuing on them yeah throwing
the law and darts that you
just
exactly.
A
Las Vegas
someone
stuck in
s
traffic in San Jose.
Wow.
Most people in San Jose are currently stuck in traffic.
Yeah.
Like literally the majority of the city.
Is at this very moment stuck in traffic.
Yeah, it'd be a tire team of the sharks.
I'm pretty sure.
It's the right.
The excuse for their performance lately, at least.
Anyway.
Yeah, we're
We're talking about election.
And what it means and what it doesn't mean, and as you probably guessed from our trigger
warning, we'll be saying that although many of our Calvinist friends keep using that word,
it does not mean what they think it means.
And for those of you who thought we were going to be talking about the American presidential
election.
What's wrong with you? Why would you tune in to hear more about that? Like seriously?
bunch of addicts like after the last couple of weeks you want to hear more about that, right? Like
I hope all of you listed a got the joke and knew that wasn't what we were actually talking about
um there's someone out there that's really angry right now because we just bait and switched them
Yes, I'm sure I'm sure but trust me there are a couple of other places
they could go to get information about that at the present time, 24, 24 hours straight
if they want to. From myriad perspectives. C-SPAN, after dark. C-SPAN was great back
when they did book notes. Oh, I never saw that. Oh, book notes was like, so that's what
they did on the weekends and right when Congress wasn't in session because they had
nothing to broadcast. So they had two things in the morning they had this
college show where they didn't have the calls screened. So it was a lot of people
calling in and cussing and sneaking out of the air and causing trouble. And then
the rest of the day they had C-SPAN book notes which was like book events from
all over the countries. Mostly politics and prose in Washington DC. But lots of
other Hoi D20 uppity bookstores you know and people.
going to do their presentations. People with their books about World War II and some listeners
grandpa was one of the five people there who got up to challenge the guy who wrote the book
during the Q and A time. That kind of book of it. But it was majestic because they were doing
see span book notes on cable at a time in my life when you'll stay on a
Saturday.
I had been up all night the night before and man if you need something to help you go to sleep.
That's the one huh.
C-SPAN booking outs.
Wow.
Low you right into it.
Sort of perfect for that.
Sunday afternoon nap.
Boom.
Put you right out.
Um.
So we were not talking about that kind of election.
We're not talking about Congress either.
see there. Oh, we have.
I'm not kidding about this. The Philadelphia Council of clergy is tuning in.
The entire council. I don't know. I mean, it's a YouTube account. It says
Philadelphia Council of clergy. Not a representative, but they have convened to
let me assume it's all of them. So hello, Philadelphia Council of clergy. If it's
in Philly, they probably got some Westminster representation there. We probably
got us some Calvinists. Yeah, this could go sideways.
Okay, so in general, what are we talking about when we're talking about election?
Right?
So, usually, the word elect, if it isn't translated as elect and English translations of
the Bible is translated as chosen.
Yeah.
Those are just that kind of used as English synonyms in translation.
And what are we here?
chosen in English, right? Like the chosen people. Yeah. Has it?
It was chosen. These people are elect picked. Yes, that's what we tend to think. We tend to think
picked that there were a group of options. And one of them was selected. Right.
elected as it were which is related but not the same word as elected yeah
um
and so
So this of course very much plays into where, and we'll be talking about this in more detail obviously later,
where are Calvinist friends and others before them, and since probably have taken the idea of that word,
that
When you hear that someone is chosen or elect
in Scripture that means God has
has chosen them, generally chosen them,
you know, from eternity for something
and it's gonna end up to mostly be salvation.
Right. Right.
That they're chosen for.
We'll get into that more later.
But the word, actual words in Hebrew and Greek
have a little more nuance to them on one hand
And on the other hand, are a little more flexible.
So, it's worth noting that the words we're talking about in Hebrew and Greek are, in both
cases, are adjectives.
Yeah.
And it'll become clear as we talk why that's so important.
Yes.
They are not participles.
So a part is simple for people who have graduated high school and forgotten.
their English classes, as most people other than Father Andrew do quite quickly.
Yeah, I mean, this is what people think majoring in English is about.
Yeah.
It's like grammar and stuff.
Yeah, it's not.
You're reading literature.
But yeah.
Right.
That's it.
But I only know because you're studying foreign languages.
A participle is a language thing.
when you take a verb and you subsidize it.
meaning you take the verb to choose, for example.
And you turn that into an adjectival phrase
like the one who was chosen, the one who was picked.
Yeah.
Right, the one who had this verb done to them.
Right?
So it's of key importance that neither Hebrew nor in Greek
are we talking about a verbal structure
That is.
the one who had this action done to them by God or someone else.
Yeah, it's like it's like the word employee, right? That's the, you know, you've got
employee employee, the one who is employed. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So this is an adjective
which describes the person. In the case of...
Hebrew were talking about the word bacheer. Not to be confused with bacheer as in Julian
bacheer. Yeah, or bacheer always wanted to be one of the chosen but he was genetically modified.
So right, that's what I'm saying.
Yeah.
He was built to be neurotic.
But so but here.
in Hebrew is used to mean something more like given a role or set apart for a
purpose or assigned or given an office.
Right?
So...
But again, it's an adjective.
Yeah, so it is a word that's used to describe the person who is assigned an office or a role or a task, right?
Not just to indicate that they have been assigned that role or that task, but to describe the person who has been assigned that role or that task.
We find basically the same thing in Greek.
So there is a verb, eclegomy.
Or a Klegelme, which like literally means, you know, spoken out.
Yes.
Yeah.
And so you could try and butterfly it and say called out or to call out.
But that gets, there is an adjective form of it.
So again, it is not the participle form of that verb.
It is an adjective for the same root, a klektos.
Yeah, which is where we get our word of clectic?
And that means can mean sort of roughly called out, but it's more like identified.
Yeah, like identified from a group for a purpose.
Right, we've tagged this guy.
Okay.
As I mentioned, both of these are adjectives.
These account for the vast majority of uses of these words.
it's
Right.
Different words are used when you're talking about like someone choosing to do something.
These aren't the same words.
Now that said, that said, I'm going to do a sorry non-calvinist here, say just to prove
how even-handed we are.
So...
There's a certain species of anti-Calvinist out there of whom latent flowers as an example.
And latent flowers is a Baptist.
He's like the Texas Baptist Association.
Their head of evangelism or something similar.
And uh, Late Forest is also one of those dudes.
like Mitt Romney, who kind of looks like a Sears catalog model from the early 80s.
Like that particular kind of like handsome dude like from that era. Yeah, everybody knows that
I'm talking about like Mitt Romney like Layton Flat like. Right, right. Yeah, you know,
like on the Simpsons, I'm TV's Troy McCluer. Yeah, yeah. Like he would be in the catalog like
like looking down at his watch, modeling the suit, right?
That's right, exactly.
So, but he has to his credit picked up on the fact that this is an adjective, right,
not a participle.
This is not talking about the recipient of some action from God or someone else, but
it's talking about a quality of the person.
the example he is given, or I describe this in
It's like USDA choice meat.
That is so choice.
So someone who's chosen they're just like really choice.
Right?
They're just like really great.
Yeah.
No.
That is not what it means.
I mean, good attempt to find another use for the word choose or choice other than the one
on Calvinist's use, but that's the wrong one.
Yeah. Yeah.
So, but at least I said he was handsome, right?
So, say that's, I mean,
those are no one he's talking about on this point, but handsome.
He's no William Shender.
Well,
as it is 90s, you know,
yeah.
So, what are some examples?
Words, obviously, have meaning based on their usage, right?
Right.
So we want...
already started setting forth a claim that this is talking about a particular quality
of a person that causes them to be set aside for a purpose or to be given a particular role.
One are some examples of these terms being used in the Hebrew Bible in the Christian Old
Testament.
So one of the obvious...
and most probably the first one people think of.
Right. Well, if you said to someone, if we're on matchgame with
Gene Rayburn, I said chosen blank. The chosen people, right? And
you're trying to match with like Phyllis Diller and Paul
Lind and Charles Nelson Riley, right? Wow. A good option would
be to pick people. Right? Yeah. Chosen Black. Right.
Um, so Israel, right, the Old Testament is God's chosen people.
That's maybe where your your brain first goes. Right.
And that is obviously right.
The adjective is used.
Yeah.
Drive Israel a lot.
And people people from that, they get this idea of like saying that, you know,
Israel is picked by God, you know, from all the other nations, you know, like,
Who do they think is-
Some people even say, well, who do they think they are?
You know, that sort of thing.
Saying a side, of course, the big problem of what is Israel.
But yeah, there's this idea of, you know,
God looked at all the nations and said,
ah, I like this one the best.
Yes.
I'm going to pick this one and I'm going to,
I love them more than all the other ones.
And they're special.
Right.
And just because I chose.
Okay, this is end.
Side note to Calvinists as we get going.
See, I was about to say chose arbitrarily.
If you say to Calvinists that God makes this choice arbitrarily in their system, they
get really mad.
But I mean, that's what, and they say it's not arbitrarily.
It's according to his good pleasure.
It's according to his will.
Guys, the word arbitrio in Latin means will.
What?
arbitrary means.
chosen with reference to nothing but one's will. Okay. Arbitrary is exactly what you say it is.
Like, definitionally, arbitrary, derived from the light arbitrary, reads just exactly what you say. So
in the Caledist system, got to use this arbitrarily, choose according with reference to nothing, but as well.
Just will did picked Israel, right? Well, there's a problem with that.
There's a problem with that.
When you...
read Hebrew Bible, read the Old Testament closely, and that's that Israel is not one of the 70 nations.
Yeah, you look at the list of the 70 nations that come of Noah's sons, read through the list.
Israel is not there. Yeah, this is in Genesis 10, table of nations. Yeah, just read it.
Israel is not one of the nations. Israel is something other than the nations. Right,
definitely.
Yeah. Right. The Latin word for the nations is Gentiles, right? And most of our English translations
don't translate that in the New Testament. Sometimes they do in the Old Testament. Sometimes they
translate Gentiles. Yeah. Translating is the nations, right? So Israel isn't one of the nations. There's
Israel and then there's the nations, right? And so Israel is not one of the nations.
God doesn't choose one of the nations.
creates Israel. Yeah and it creates Israel sometime. I can argue about how much
time, but sometime after the dispersing of the nations at Bable. And that's true
whether you want to talk about God creating Israel from Abraham. Abraham is from
or
Abraham is a person who belonged to one of the nations who is
Called out of that nation to become the father of Israel. Yeah, God did not pick the nation that Abraham had been part of
right
Yeah
And Abraham by himself as a Samaria
Yeah, not Samarians not as a variance. Yes
But Abraham and he's called to leave Samaria
Right, so it's made pretty obvious that that's not what's going on
Yeah.
Or if you want to talk about, right, which would be sort of the nascent beginning of Israel,
or if you want to talk about the Exodus, if you want to talk about Matt's side, I, which
is what the lyrics now, this nation has been formed by God that has a new identity.
And that's what in the later, in the prophets, in the Old Testament, they're going to refer
to that event as the birth of Israel, right?
So if you want to look at that as a beginning of Israel, you've got this.
Hodgepodge group that is in our modern terms ethnically mixed. They didn't have that concept, but that is now made into the nation of Israel.
They were not a people. God made them a people. Right.
But so Israel collectively is for
to their at Mount Sinai by the giving of the Torah and they are given a history. When Israel is
formed, they are all Abraham's sons. It doesn't matter if that was literally true. They didn't know
that DNA existed. Yeah. They didn't even have a concept of heredity by the way.
I mean, there were far from understanding DNA and that kind of thing.
Caleb is the elder of the tribe of Judah.
It doesn't matter that he and his father were kinocytes.
And therefore no relation to the person Judah.
He's a member of the tribe of Judah, Judah's his father.
That's how this works.
So they're given this history.
They're given this common family when they are
But Israel is a whole, therefore it's not picked.
It's created.
And by the way, this is telegraphing where we're going later,
But what made someone put an Israelite or not?
someone part of that nation that God created or not, what made them one of the chosen or
not was whether they participated in the Passover ritual.
Yeah, were they circumcised, participated in the Passover, doing the things?
My first generation, it was literally participating in the Passover ritual.
Yeah, yeah.
Right, marking their doorpost.
It was something they did.
But we'll come back to that.
Right now we're surveying the waste chosen as used.
You'll test them it. So in what sense then is Israel as a whole chosen?
Right, they're not chosen as in picked. There are all these different nations and God picked this one
because they get created. But there is something different about them with regards to the rest of the nations.
Right. What is that adjective doing? That adjective right by here that we translate is chosen. What is it doing?
Okay, well.
You can see that Israel is created and it is set aside and called to a particular purpose
in relationship to the nations. So it has a unique role or a unique purpose.
And we've talked about this before on the show that that ultimately what that role and that purpose is
is priesthood.
Right, they are to be a kingdom of priests, as they're told in the Torah, priests for who?
Right? A priest represents God to non-priests and represents non-priests to God.
So the nation is a whole were to be priests to the nations, to the other nations.
They're supposed to represent God to the other nations.
they were supposed to represent the other nations to God.
And on the piece of representing God to the nations, that meant they had to live their life in a different way than all the other nations.
This is why there are most of the commandments given in the Torah are only given to the nation of Israel and not to everyone.
They're not supposed to stop other people from eating pork.
They're supposed to not eat pork like other people do.
They're called to a different way of life, to a higher way of life as a way of representing
who the true God is to the other nations.
And then exhibit A of them representing the nations before God is at the piece of tabernacles
when they go and they offer the 70 bulls for the 70 nations.
They offer these sacrifices to God for those nations.
Yeah, which is pretty interesting as unique to Israel, like which other of the nations are offering sacrifices for a different nation, especially to their own God.
You know like this is something that is uniquely Israel right and is
Something given by God that demonstrates this
that he's different than those other gods.
Right? The only reason another nation would have
to sacrifice to Israel's goddess
because they wanted something from him.
Yeah, right.
Right? Otherwise, he's not their god, he's Israel's god.
Right?
But the idea that sacrifice needs to be made
for all those nations to this god
means doesn't just imply, it means
that he is the god of all of those nations as well.
That's built into the built into the system. Now
19th century German friends rear their ugly heads again. This is a whole lot of sorry so and so
Yeah, there's a lot of sorry so and so's out there right now
Sorry, I don't know why that caught me so funny because you may you may go out and pick up a commentary on the
and I can have a commentary on the viticus.
You may look up this piece of tabernacles thing.
Odds are good.
That they're going to tell you, or at least point out, the going theory that, oh, actually,
actually, since ancient Israel was really, we all know was really pagan, that they were
offering bowls to the gods of those other nations.
which kind of begs the question like so they they Google up all the nations that are gods. I
got to thank you for running this. They have some kind of diptics of who the current most high god
was at each of the 70 nations. It checked in with all their ambassadors. So they so they know who
to sacrifice it to. So that that that dog don't hunt that don't make no sense. Right in the first
place. And this also has the very common problem with all of these theories of like, oh oops,
Look!
the editors of Leviticus let slip that they were really pagans like they once again they just didn't notice something
Yeah
Like really
Right
Like these this priestly cast after the exile they were rubbing their hands together like ah we will convince them all that we were always
Watteos and
They oops these texts that have been being this to another thing hundreds of years
with super care.
which they are copying, right?
They themselves are copying.
Yeah.
And they're the only ones who can read.
I know.
They just miss this stuff.
Yeah.
Right?
Can't make this up, folks.
That's, uh...
I just, I don't have that
critical scholar, uh, bone, I guess.
Right, like...
Actually, I kind of can't a couple of times I've tried to come up with something like that
as parody and then found out somebody really published an article.
You can't satirize anymore.
Yes, yeah, like because you make something up and then you know as a joke and then someone
out there is doing it unironically.
Yes, yeah.
So as David Hume said, there's no philosophy so absurd that some philosopher is not
proposed.
it. Yeah, so where are some places? There's lots of places where this adjective is used to describe
Israel. I would point to a few of the Isaiah is particularly thick with them. If you're a 19th
century German particularly Deuteron, Isaiah. But like Isaiah 41 verse 8, Isaiah 41...
24 verse 1 Isaiah 45 verse 4. Interestingly in all three of those contacts, God is referring
to Israel as his chosen, but in none of those three is he particularly happy with them.
Hmm.
Yeah, it's not like I love these people best.
Yeah.
These people are kind of the worst, but their mind is more.
It's like when Obi-Wan says to Anakin, you were the chosen one.
Oh, come on, I mean, kid, I referenced the worst, the very worst of the Star Wars.
That is not the worst of the Star Wars.
Oh, okay.
Actually, I think by a million miles that it's not a good one.
I think a attack of the clones is probably the worst.
That may be like the fifth best.
Wow.
Like fan to menace, first of all, is the worst of the prequels.
You think so, huh?
By a country mile.
I think episode two is
the worst of prequels. Honestly. No, it's mid. It's so wooden. But all of it is because
George Lucas wasn't really directing anymore. Yeah. Just pulling it in. Well, people don't
remember that he didn't direct Empire Strikes Back in return to the Jedi. Right. Right.
I direct the first one. Yeah. Yeah. But now with this, these Star Wars out like, I know,
three shines like the stars of heaven.
compared to Holy cow rise of Skywalker. You were the chosen one, but you you have made me mad
and so therefore I will let you go into flames and lava. He pointed out the great truth that once
you have the high ground, it's over. It's true in all forms of life. I repeat that line. Every time
one of my dogs will jump up onto the bed, while the other dog is down below, it's like it's over.
She has the high-gramp.
Yeah.
Yeah. Speaking of high ground, Chosen is also used to refer to Jerusalem.
It was adjective is used to refer to Jerusalem as the Chosen City.
Yep. That may be less familiar to people.
I mean, like if you put that on match game, maybe you'd match with Ruth Busy.
I don't know
you get like one point. But a couple of good examples of that are in first Kings 1132 and 1421
or third kingdoms using the orthodox city Bible. And the idea there is Jerusalem is chosen,
is the chosen city because the temple is there and so God has placed his name there. Yeah,
Although that's what his presence is.
for the spirit is. Yeah, but I mean, remember everybody God did not like choose for the temple to be
there. He sort of was okay with it when they when they built it, but ultimately he was, you know,
about the tabernacle, but yeah, yeah. Yeah. In the in the broad sense of divine providence.
Yes, yes, right. But within the narrative, right within the narrative.
of first and second Kings or third and fourth kingdoms, right?
Within that narrative, God does not like command them to build a temple for him and Jerusalem.
David gets the idea to do that.
God tells David he can't, his son will, Solomon builds it, and then if you read the prayer,
God sort of in his response to Solomon's prayer, acquiesces.
Right.
to play psych well okay
Right, but this is not a case where out of all the cities God picked this one and told them to put a temple there
That's not what happens in fact if you're gonna make an argument
For what where God picked it would probably be Shiloh
Hmm actually read
First and second Samuel closely
But anyway, yeah
So again, chose it
is this adjective describing the place because this city has this special role of being
the host to the temple of God. Now, it is also used for subgroups of people, meaning groups
of people within Israel are referred to as chosen. So Israel as a whole is chosen, but
but then also there are subgroups at various points.
or a month.
Joe's.
That's the, uh, what is, what is higher than USDA choice?
Uh, is prime higher than choice?
Uh, I don't know.
Come on, man.
You don't know.
I buy meat.
Look, I buy my meat from a farm out in northwestern Pennsylvania.
Like, there's no like stamps and primes and choices on it.
You know, yeah.
You don't have to go half a pig.
It fills up my friends.
to test the agriculture.
of the end of Aptis.
Actually, it's a big clan of Catholics that I buy from out there, in fact.
That was me throwing another bone to...
That was a deep cut reference for our Calvinist fans.
See, I got some form too.
I buy my milk from Anabaptists.
Yeah, men and nights.
Yeah, but I buy my cows and pigs from Catholics.
What can I say?
Yes, well, every good Dutchman...
to test their errors. So we do, by the way, have one person who's tuning in from the Netherlands.
So, well, I was to believe one of the chosen people. Yes.
So, yeah. So one example of chosen being used for one of these subgroups of people is in
Numbers chapter one verse sixteen. Everyone's favorite book, the Book of Numbers.
But it refers to the elders of the people, right?
The 70 or 72 elders as the chosen, right?
These are the those chosen to be the elders of the people.
And then it says, who are the chiefs among the tribes?
So these people were already tribal chiefs, like Roman Reigns or Solosiko.
And yet they're then, quote unquote, chosen to be elders, to be the elders of the people
assisting Moses.
Right?
So how is chosen working there?
Like clearly God didn't pick them.
They were already kind of in the position.
Well, Moses did, right?
It wasn't like, okay, I'm going to pick who's going to be a charge.
I pay.
the people who are already in charge. Right. Right. That has to make a lot of sense. Right. So
what this is saying is what chosen is doing there. What's the word again translated as chosen.
What it's doing there is it's talking about those people who had been the chiefs within the tribes
were made the elders of the people. They were given this role. They were put into this office.
Right?
This body, this governing body was constituted by the people who were the chiefs of the various tribes.
Yeah. Right. So this, this is what's going to ultimately become the Sanhedrin, but this first batch, these are the people who are already chiefs of the tribes.
They weren't sort of people elected chosen at random, most instant sort of look around the, the semi-annights and say, I like the cup of cut of that guy's jib.
You're on the council, right?
This was, there are already leaders.
But by far the most common way that this term chosen is used to describe a group
within Israel is to describe a military unit.
Hmm.
This adjective is described used to describe Israel's army.
Yeah, several places in the Old Testament actually.
Yes.
You're given some number.
Sometimes a ludicrous number
Like 180,000 in one case.
180,000 chosen.
They are the chosen.
Yes.
And you can see this in places like judges 20 verse 34 for Samuel 24 verse two for Samuel 26 verse two.
Second Samuel 6 verse one first Kings 12 verse 21.
He's the orthodox study Bible, you know, first kingdom, second kingdoms, third kingdoms.
Um.
You let me suggest.
that 180,000 chosen doesn't mean that say David went and picked 180,000 people.
I mean he could have been a heck of a recruiter out of, right, but recruiting isn't the same as picking.
You know, I know I'm just saying, right? Like, that's, yeah, I mean that's, right? These names down.
Yeah, that's a mustering. That's a mustering. It's not a picking. Right. Right.
And in fact, if you-
look at 2 Samuel 6 verse 1, for example, one of those off the list, right? It says that David
gathered the chosen or no, this is it's all, Saul gathers the chosen. Yeah, not that he chose the
chosen. Right. The verb is gathered chosen is an adjective. Right. Right. So he takes all of those
who have this quality of being the chosen and he gathers them all up to take them to war.
He musters them, right? He gathers them all up.
So chosen here, right, that verb that we translate chosen is referring to certain kinds of qualifications, right?
What is that? Well, there's no, there are no standing armies in the ancient world in this period.
Okay. In this period of antiquity.
The army, your army is called up and it consists of the able
a lot of men in a certain age range, right?
Who you gather them all up to make war?
That's your fighting force.
Yeah, they're not professional soldiers.
Yeah, there aren't, there are little bands
of professional mercenaries who travel around,
like David forms one of those for a while
when he goes to fight for the Philistines and stuff.
But that's not, your national army is not those guys, right?
If you get afford to hire some of those guys,
you set the
up as commanders over the 12,000 farmers. You've placed a pool together between the ages of 18 and
35. Who are your army? This is what the gathering is gathering those people up. What does it mean that
that those people are chosen, what means they meet those qualifications?
Yeah.
They're here because they-
meat, they're able-bodied, right? If they're not able-bodied, they're not.
Yeah, they're a certain cohort, right? They're a, yeah. So they're qualified to
then have this role as a fighting man, right? And so we're working our way
down. You find a lot. This is not so much in the New Testament.
The idea is in the New Testament, but the phrase is not the New Testament.
But what you find a lot in Second Table Jewish literature is that the term, the elect one,
is used interchangeably with the term the anointed one, i.e. Messiah.
Yeah.
Right.
And of course, anointed, what does the anointed mean in there?
It means anointed to be king, anointed to be the Messiah, anointed to be the purpose.
or to be a priest.
Right.
And so here, but here is being set up as synonymous with that, right?
The one given this office, right?
This one who has singled out, who has identified, who has, right?
So it's clearly serving that purpose there, right?
It's not, again, and especially as Christians, we would have to say, God did not sort of look
Look at all the people and choose one of them to be the Messiah.
Right
Let's hear an adoptionist
adoptionist or just yeah Jewish and not a Christian right maybe that'll work right yeah
but
Yeah, that that
That dog don't hunt sorry adoptionist that might be our first sorry adoptionist in the whole podcast over four years
It doesn't come I know someone who kind of is one
Um, uh, button.
kind of. So yeah, so there's a place where pretty clearly a Calvinist being a Christian
of a type would would have to say the elect being something different. But now we come
to what to me kind of ruins the whole thing.
Yeah, what does it mean?
when in the New Testament they talk about elect angels.
Well, it's St. Paul who says it in the New Testament.
Yes, I don't think they is his chosen pronoun.
So, pretty sure he's a he's just the quality of his pronoun.
You and your liberal sensibilities over here.
It's the royal they, the apostolic we.
Yeah, first Timothy 5
21, say Paul refers to the elect angels.
The elect angels.
But that phrase, the elect angels is all over the place in Second Temple literature.
Yeah.
See, there's a way for you.
And you said in the New Testament.
Anyway.
So in Second Temple literature, a lot of times when it's used, it's pretty clear how it's
being used, because the elect angels are referred to in kind of martial contexts.
So, in depictions of sort of the final cosmic battle between the Messiah and Belial, right,
it refers to Messiah coming with the elect angels, while we saw how elect was used for
like a military unit.
Right.
Yeah.
So it would be sort of the angels who have that role, right, or sometimes it's used to refer
to like Cherbim and Seraphim who have this particular role or status.
But again, it's very clear that it has to sort of mean something like that, right?
Like, it can't mean like the Calvinist version of what that word elect or chosen me.
Yeah, because within Calvinism it's about God picking certain people.
to be saved and then picking other people not to be saved. Right. Now, now we should say
that this is an inherited, at least part of it is an inherited view. Calvin did not make
up the core setup. Yeah, before we dive into that. Yeah, yeah. Right. Because someone might have said
when we just said, well wait, can somebody say, well why not?
Yeah, right. There might be somebody out there who said,
why not would you say, yeah, God, God chose which angels would
remain loyal and which ones would fall? Right. But why is that a
problem? Because that's what we're going to get into now. Yeah,
there's no salvation for angels. Right. We're going to explain to
you why that's a problem in terms of the Calvinist understanding
of election. Yeah. Um, so yeah, we're getting into super and
infrared or lap serianism. So say what you want Calvinist, you can
like us we have not known.
what I'm talking about. So yes, this father Andrew said before I cut him off, as I so often
do, you do. The, oh, don't be a sad sack about it. So this is not, people think of Calvinism
as predestinarianism, right?
Predestinarianism is actually a very...
small part of Calvinism. Yeah, it's a big Calvinism is a whole bunch of stuff is a whole system of thought and belief and
piety. It's not just the sotyreology. Right. Right. It has let alone just the pre-design.
Eucharistic theology has it's like there's all kinds of stuff. This is why reformed baptists aren't really
reformed in art real Calvinists. See here we go. I'm great favor with some of the Calvinists. You have chosen some of them.
Yes, I've chosen some of the Calvinist to curry favor with while the elected
putting down some others.
Um.
See, I mean, hey, if you give me Presbyterians versus Reformed Baptist, I got aside with the Presbyterians.
Right.
You got to baptize them babies.
Anyway, they do a better architecture as well.
Um.
So, yeah, so in terms of
of what John Calvin himself says about predestination and reprobation. Reprobation is the other side.
Right? And you need to be clear, Calvin very clearly accepted both. The Calvinist tradition
at large has accepted both. God chooses people to give eternal life and salvation. God
chooses people according to them.
to damn to eternal torment.
Yeah. Right? That's, that's it. That's there.
Now the Lutherans, right? The Lutherans.
They're a little more dodgy, a little harder to nail down.
They say God chooses people to save, but He doesn't choose people.
To damn. Right. He just fails to choose them to save.
You, you figure out how that works.
Yeah.
But that's a Lutheran thing.
Those guys are like Jello sometimes you can't nail them to a wall.
Can't nail them down.
But the Calvinist Richard very clearly says both, right?
But that said Calvin gets his view of predestined
area is from the Dominicans.
Okay.
He is not really an innovator on that particular front.
Now when you get to some of the
secondary doctrines related to election and reprobation, like limited atonement and stuff,
their Calvin goes in a different direction, okay?
But predestination and reprobation itself, he's getting from the Dominican tradition within
Roman Catholicism.
To the point that if you go and read, and I do not recommend doing this, you know, I give
to the Presbyterians and now I take away.
I don't recommend going and trying to read the Westminster standards. It is so boring.
It is like...
It is English scholasticism. It is like the most boring possible form of document, right? Like
everything tedious and dry about scholasticism mixed with everything tedious and dry about English
philosophy.
like in one place.
But if, for some reason for a class or something,
you have to read the Westminster standards.
Or if you just go and look up the statement
in the Westminster standards about reprobation,
about people being chosen for eternal damnation,
it is straight plagiarized from the sumithaologica
of Thomas Aquinas.
Like you would get kicked out of school
if you turned in the Westminster standards.
Yeah, they take
you cheated off of Old Thomas's paper. Now it's important though, right? As I said,
once you get to the ancillary stuff that flows from that Calvin goes and the Calvinist tradition
after him, going in a different direction. So for Thomas, and yes, I can't believe I'm the one
someone who has to tell people this.
Okay.
Okay, you refer to him as Thomas.
Aquinas is not his last name.
Oh, yeah, that's where he's from.
It means from Akino.
Akino, yeah.
Okay.
Like, if you're lowest lane, calling Clark Kent Smallville.
Okay, that works.
But people don't call me Lathe yet.
They don't call me Redlands where I grew up.
Okay, like, what's up Redlands?
Right, yes, that's not a thing.
I don't know, I feel like we should call you there.
You want me to just call you Guam?
I did live there for five years.
Old Guam over there.
So, right.
So you referred him as Thomas.
Anyway, that's why they're called Tomas.
Not a keenness.
Sorry.
End of that particular rant.
Why is this me?
Why aren't the Roman Catholics straightening people out on this?
Falling down on your jobs.
Um.
So what Thomas is doing, part of what triggers this rant, by the way, dear listeners, is
that Father Andrew referred to him as a quietness in the notes.
I know, I know.
I'm not safe in my own home.
It's always a good day when I can trigger you.
What Thomas is trying to do, and again, I'm no apologist for...
But I try to be fair. So what Thomas is trying to do is he's trying to express a
synergistic relationship between God's providence and free will.
And
so for Thomas
It is true
at least in the summa, right?
I am no scholar of Thomas Aquinas.
Right?
studied him some with a sister-tian monk, so I know something but far from everything.
But Thomas is trying to express that everyone who comes to God, God has come to them.
And everyone who rejects God, God has rejected them.
But what Thomas doesn't do is he doesn't ascribe...
any kind of causal relationship between those two facts. Meaning he doesn't say, as Calvin
and the Calvinist tradition will, and the Jansinists did, that God's accepting or rejecting someone
and caused them to accept or reject God.
But he also doesn't say the opposite.
it, right? He also doesn't say that someone accepting God caused God to accept them or someone
rejecting God caused God to reject them as if they were operating independently and could apply this
causal thing to God, right? So there is for Thomas an absolute correlation between those things,
but no relationship of causation.
You can decide for yourself how
that works. Doesn't really do it for me. I don't think it's a necessary distinction to make.
I think the distinctions he's having to make are because he's gone down this sort of scholastic
trail of making a bunch of other previous distinctions, right? So he's he's kind of trying to solve
problems that he created for himself with his views on other topics. Yeah, ultimately.
And he's trying, Thomas is trying really hard in the suit.
to reconcile St. Augustine with the other church fathers.
And by reconcile, I mean, trying to make it so that they're all saying the same thing.
And there are places where they just manifoldly disagree.
Right. St. John Cashett, for example, just disagreed with St. Augustine about some things on this very topic.
Right, but so Thomas is very much his
approach is always to try and reconcile everybody. No, no, they're all really getting at the
same thing, right? Really understand them right. And so that again creates a whole bunch
of problems for himself that he wouldn't have if he'd just say, well, okay, some of these
places where they disagree, say to gust and didn't get it right, then you don't have to
trying to tie all those knots. Yeah. But so that Dominican view precedes.
John Calvin and the Calvinist tradition.
There's other folks got chalk.
There's there's a whole thing here.
I'm not good to
literally about that.
You need to send an email to Dr.
Cyril Jenkins about this.
That's who you need to send.
Ask him all about got chalk.
Wow.
You tell somebody to send email to someone besides me.
So what other than you?
I don't think you know what got chalk is.
I think you think got chalk is a department store.
So I mean...
sounds like a German person to me. But yeah, go bother. We have a lot of names like that in the
series that I live in. We have all these Germans. Go bother Dr. Dr. Cyril Jenkins about this. He would
love, I think, to type you a 2000 word email, explain a gott talk. It is relationship to pre-destinaried
But I will pass over that in silence at this point.
So.
But I want to try to be fair to the Calvinists even as we're picking on them.
But so Calvin makes this, the Dominican view, is sort of a plank then in a more to get
me fair to Calvin.
In some ways, a more logically consistent system, right, where Thomas is trying to hold a
a bunch of things in tension.
because he wants to reconcile everybody.
Caled feels free to just choose one
of the two conflicting things, right?
To go one way instead of the other
and not try to reconcile it.
Just say one was right, the other was wrong.
On these topics, he basically says,
St. Augustine was right.
But to other topics, he says St. Augustine was wrong,
but he's willing to sort of pick a winner on any given topic.
A winner is you.
But so...
Keep in mind, we're explaining what the problem is with elect angels.
Where are we again?
Yeah, yeah.
We're going to get there.
What's the problem with God just picking which angels are going to be faithful and which ones are going to fall?
So, within Calvinism, right,
the structure of salve-
is very carefully articulated on the divine end.
When we get into the second half, we're going to talk about on the human end,
like the golden chain of redemption, as they call it, and end.
Right, sort of how a human is saved. That's on the human side.
The divine side we're talking about from a Calvinist perspective,
God's plan of salvation.
So this is
in eternity, in eternity past whatever that means or various ways. As we've talked about
before on the show, I think you can't really do any of this Calvinist stuff if you really
remove the temporal element, but if you talk to Calvinists, they will insist there is
no temporal element. They are talking about the logical order of God's decrees in his
in the mind of God.
They have mapped out. They have not mind of God mapped out. Yes. There's some wobbly
trinitarianism here too in terms of the mind of God and who that one person is. But we
will, we don't need to go into that now either.
So, and the reason this is important, the reason this is important.
for Calvinists is that, right, I mean, it may sound if you're not a Calvinist, it may sound absurd to you
possibly rightly so, that any human thinks they know the logical order of God's decrees in his own mind, right?
Maybe rightly so, right? But again, our Calvinists friends would say, well, God has in certain ways
revealed this to us, right? So that would be their counter-argument.
And the core thing, so the core issue here is, a Calvinist friend's most of them, most
of them do not want to make God the author of evil.
They don't want to make God the cause of evil in the world.
Sure, I mean, that's most of all though.
Yeah, there are some that be like, yeah, God created evil.
Yes, we're basically...
consistent and we'll just say yes every evil horrific nightmarish thing that
has ever happened God before he created the world declared that that would
happen and made it happen right. Points were consistency I guess but most of
them right and so when faced and this is a little bit of a jab I admit it but they
can take some jobs.
The general Calvinist tactic when someone points out the logical outcome of these kind of beliefs,
like they say, well, that would make God the other way. Right? Is to make a distinction.
Yeah. And so the real purpose of talking about the order of these decrees in the mind of God
is to make certain distinctions. Right? So one of those distinctions is between
Inferlapse serianism and...
super lap serenism. You may be thinking we're in rarefied air here, but I was for a time
in possession. I passed them on for historic preservation, literally, of a set of bulletins
from Reverend Danhoff's Church in Michigan.
Who was...
part of a split within the Dutch reform church. They were his weekly bulletins from the 1920s.
And the bulletins are like half in Dutch and half in English.
Right? We're actually more Dutch. Most of the English is like the Bible and the Dutch is like all
all the announcements of the community stuff.
And each of them has sort of a-
The theology note, a little theology note on the back for these Dutch farmers, right,
to help them learn some things about the faith, right?
The Dutch reform faith.
One of them is about the difference between inferlapse serian and superlapse serianism.
Amazing.
I always get that mixed up.
I have to go look it up every time.
I know.
I mean, these are just not words that I tend.
I use some words, you know, but these are not words that I use on the
Well, okay, so so lapses right?
Yes, that's the fall of men kind of the lat we're for the fall right?
The fall of men and so that's the the lap serian part right?
And so the question is where in God's decrees is that decree of the fall in terms of vis-a-vis election?
Right. Is it? Is it that?
God, he decreed the fall because he was decreeing election or
reprobation or did he decree the sin of man and then and then he
decreed to save some because he did that.
Yeah, right.
So, but you know clear as mud.
Okay.
It covers the ground.
No.
uh uh
In for lapsarianism, which is the majority of Calvinists
Right, right, or inferlapsarian. They would say, right, that God decreed that humanity
would fall into sin, right, because they say God decrees everything that happens. So he
decreed the fall. He decreed that Adam would sin in the garden, right, according to most
Calvinists, inferlapsarian. And then having decreed that, that all of humanity would fall into
This is it.
God then decreed that he would save some of them and decreed that the others would be
left in their sins and go on to eternal damnation. Okay? That's the majority of Calvinist view.
The minority Calvinist view, these people are sometimes described as hyper Calvinists though
a lot of times.
Hyper-Calvinist is just a word that a Calvinist used was for someone more Calvinist than them or more blunt about their Calvinism than then
Or they just don't like
Super lap serium is the idea that God decrees that he is going to reveal his glory
By
giving some creating some people and giving them eternal life and creating
other people and giving them eternal.
That's like decree one. That's pretty glorious. And so then based on the fact that that's what he wants to do,
he declares that humanity will fall into sin as a means of getting there.
Okay. So in Infra-Lapsary in the more common view, right,
Right? The reason God is...
choosing to reprobate those people is their sin, which is the product of his
decree. But still, there be reprobated because of their sin. For the super
lapisarean view, the more hyper Calvinist view, right? They're being
reprobated just to be reprobated.
For God to desp-
lay his glory by subjecting people to eternal punishment.
And then God causes them to sin in order to set them up for that punishment.
Yeah. I mean, either way.
But you can see how inferlap serenism, the more common view,
yeah, it's kind of a distinction and a dodge.
Right, right, because the sin they're reprobated for is still the result.
of God's decree. Yeah, it's just, you know, where in this, uh,
rubegoldberg is the first domino big pushed over. Okay. But so
how does any of this apply to angels? Right? For whom there is no
redemption? Yeah, it literally says, is it in Hebrews? It's not
angels that he helps. Yes. Yeah. Yes. Given everything in Hebrews,
V-Cov-E angels, right?
that the elect angels can't be talking about election in this sense.
No, they're not being saved. There's no salvation for angels.
Right. So,
pre-review here at the end of our first half, okay?
Elect isn't being used the way Calvinists use it to describe angels when it's used to describe angels.
It's not being used the way Calvinus used it when it's being used to describe.
to describe Christ, to describe the Messiah as the elect one.
It's not being used when that way, when it's used to describe the elders of Israel,
or a military unit. It's not being used the way Calvinists use it when that word is used to
describe Jerusalem as the chosen city. It's not being used that way when it's used to describe
Israel is the chosen people.
So it's not impossible. Right. It's not impossible that all of a sudden some place in the New Testament
could come along and use these same words that are used in the Old Testament and in the Hebrew Bible
in a completely different way. Right. Yeah. So maybe some of it sometimes that
Does someone come along in the New Testament?
it and just start using these words, it'll be a complete break with the old testament usage
of these words. Start using words in a different way and this could meant that's not impossible.
It happens. Right. Yeah. I mean, I can't think of any cases, but logically it is possible,
as opposed, right?
But how likely is it?
And if you're going
to go ahead and break with all the previous usage, you're going to have to have a reason
for it with the text.
And how are you going to signal that?
How is that going to be signaled in the text to say, now wait, I'm using these ideas totally
differently than they are in the Old Testament.
and let's say the someone
talking about his st. Paul, let's say the place we're talking about is the book of Romans.
What if we read what st. Paul says about this in the book of Romans?
And the way those words are used in the Old Testament were perfectly fine. In fact,
to work better to explain what St. Paul is saying.
Well then...
What then?
So yeah, yeah.
All right, well, it's been a good beefy first half.
We're going to go ahead and go to our first break here on this episode about election on Laura's Spirit's podcast.
So we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
give them a call at 855-237-2346.
855 AF Radio.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation
of the epistles of Saint Paul, disconnected from any historical reality.
The Paul operated during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish
world.
In Saint Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations, Father Stephen D. Young surveyes
Paul's life.
and writings, interpreting them within the holy tradition of the Orthodox Church.
This survey is followed by DeYoung's interpretive translation of St. Paul's Epistles, which
deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in 1st century Judaism, DeYoung hopes to unsettle commonly
held notions and help the reader reassess St. Paul in his historical context.
Available now at store.AncientFace.com.
Again.
that is store.enchantface.com.
You've probably heard of St. Rafael Halloweeny, saying to Alexander Hodevitsky, liturgical
translator Isabel Habgood, and other righteous men and women who made their mark on the
early development of Orthodoxy in America.
But what about the notorious, itinerant Bulgarian monk, or Father Rafael Morden, the first
Black Orthodox priest in America?
Vera Johnston, who served the Orthodox Church without-
renouncing hertheosophist roots. There are stories and many others, some edifying, some appalling,
all entertaining, make up the lost histories of the early decades of Orthodox Christianity
in the continental United States. Lost histories, the good, the bad, and the strange in early
American Orthodoxy by Matthew Naney out now at store.ancientfaith.com again that is
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
And we're back.
It's the second half of this episode of The Lord of Spears
we're talking about, Evolection.
So we're just gonna you know, I'm in that first time I've heard that commercial for my book. Oh, yeah
Yeah, and they're talking about how I'm like interpreting things within the Orthodox tradition
I thought I'd just engaged in rank speculation
No reliable citations and
So
Go figure I know
Yeah, so you know, we'll just go ahead and start this half also with sorry covenants
I'm sorry.
We're talking about election and in this half we're going to
Pull up a bunch of texts from Romans because let's it be Bible
That's right. There is no Calvinism without certain special texts from Romans
At least you know the predestinarian stuff
Which is whatever if they if you're gonna make the case that there is a the New Testament
some
This completely
different usage of these terms, right? This is where you got to go, right? Yeah. Yeah.
Because if they're not being used in a different way here, they're not being used in a different
way. Right. Yep. Yep. We have come to the Locust Classicus. Yeah. Exactly. So this this
half will be all exegesis all the time. Yeah. I mean, that's what I did. I said Jesus to support my
I work at B.O.G.
All's gospel.
Oh, it's a, yeah.
I like my produces.
Oh, just what's pretty is on there.
Who people tell me I am online seems to be different
than who I actually am.
Who is the real father Stephen Diaz?
Creating some cognitive dissonance.
Well, I don't know.
Let's do an in depth, like Terry Gross,
Fresh Air, Style interview now.
Just who is the real father Stephen Diaz?
Just someday you'll read about me in a Matthew namey book,
my appalling.
story. And then you'll know the truth. I am going to get him to write that book. We will
wait until you're dead, but yeah, yeah, yeah, which statistically shouldn't be that long.
Yeah, I mean hey, yeah, okay, Romans Romans chapter eight beginning with verse 28
So, here we go, here we go, 20 and 330.
And we know that for those who love God, all things work together for good, for those
who are called according to his purpose, for those whom he fornew he also predestined
to be conformed to the image of his son in order that he might be the first born among
many brothers, and those whom he predestined he also called, and those whom he called he
also justified, and those whom he justified he also glorified.
I mean it says it right there that he predestines.
them right? Okay, so that verse 28 is important. Right, we know it's given it. So we have this
sort of chain of verbs, right, predestined and then called and then justified and then glorified.
Right, this is the...
golden chain of redemption. Yeah, as it is sometimes called and sorry, sorry guys and apologies to
Fleetwood Mac, but we're going to break the chain. So where does it begin? Begins with we know that
for those who love God, all things work together for good, for those who are called according to his
purpose. Okay, so we actually have the word called appear first.
So there's something right right away.
In the quote unquote golden chain in verse 30, those whom he predestined he also called,
well here in verse 28, we have those who are called, and then we talk about them being
predestined.
But the point here that St. Paul is making, all things work together for good, meaning
coming out of the context, right?
There are sufferings in this life.
There's persecutions, there's all of these things that we suffer, but we know that all of these things are going to ultimately work together for our good.
How do we know that?
Right? How do we know that?
Well, all of the verbs,
the verses 29 and 30,
for new predestined, called justified, glorified,
are all past tense, they're all completed verbs.
Okay.
Mi
saying Paul's talking about people in the past. He's not saying this is the
present tense. Everyone who he does this to you will also do this to he will
future tense, right? These are all past tense. Right. So he's talking about actual
people in the past. Hmm. This is not just generally about right anybody. Right.
Those
who he knew before, we can see that God did this, right? Because he's offering this. That
four is a because. This is his evidence that you and I can trust that whatever's going on in
our life right now, God is going to work it to good. Yeah. How can we trust that?
Right. And also, I think it's important to note here in like in the second half of verse 29,
where it says in order that he...
might be the first born among many brothers.
You know, those he for new, he also predestined
be conformed to the image of his son in order that he
might be the first born among many brothers.
I mean, isn't this talking about the coming of the Messiah?
Right.
Yeah.
And so we're conformed to his image.
We cover his brothers, meaning we're adopted
as sons of God.
Right.
So,
this is, he's,
St. Paul is not saying,
Oh, well, you can be confident.
Everything's gonna turn out-
Okay, because I'm going to lay out a theological principle for you here.
No.
Right.
That says that everything's going to work out.
Okay.
I'm going to repeat myself.
Right.
No, he's pointing to actual people.
Yeah.
Right.
In the Old Testament, in the Hebrew Bible.
We can see the course of their life.
Right.
Those who we knew before back in the past.
Now the word here that translated predestined, by the way,
is pro or reads
which means it means to put things in order in advance.
And the putting in order, the Orizo part, that Greek verb,
was most commonly used again as a military term for putting a military,
arraying a military information.
Right? The idea is God puts things in an order in advance.
He put things in order in advance.
so that those people who he knew before could be conformed to the image of his son,
right so that they could become like Christ.
So that Christ could be the first born among many brothers.
Right. Well, what does that mean? Well, think about it. For you or I define salvation.
Right. Christ was incarnate long, long time ago.
Yeah, before I existed.
Right. That hadn't happened. I couldn't be conformed to his image.
Right. I couldn't receive the adoption as the Son of God.
But
If Christ hadn't lived the life of it, if he hadn't died on the cross, if he hadn't risen
again, all of those things, God did before I existed from the way we experienced time
as humans.
All of that had to be put in place in advance.
All of that had to be arranged in advance.
And not just that, right?
Scriptures had to be handed down.
The church had to continue to exist.
All of these things had to happen.
And we can go back before that, all the things that led up to the incarnation of Christ, everything
recorded into the Old Testament, all the way back to the creation of the world. All that
stuff had to happen to make it possible for me today to find salvation and Christ to experience
theosis which is what St. Paul's talking about. And God put that all in order so that
that could happen.
Say, Paul, say because of that.
Here's reason one. God did all that. Right? So just because you're suffering now, you don't have to worry that this is all going to be for not. Yeah. Right.
Yeah, he's not laying out like a theory. But they're saying, look at what happened. And yeah.
And then part two of that in verse 30, he says, and look at those people.
Right. Everything that was all set up. And then he called those people.
He called Abraham out of Ur.
He called those people to put blood on their doorposts.
It would become part of Israel.
Yeah, he says he justified.
He put them right.
Yeah, and the ones he justified.
He said the call of the gospel to us.
Right.
And then yes, he put them right.
Yeah.
And he ultimately glorified them.
Right.
the way that was also there.
Do not have any aspect of temporal succession.
Yeah, in Greek.
These are not like steps.
Right.
Yeah, it's like all of these things are true.
It's like saying that man is tall and also he has brown hair
and also he has two limbs, you know, two arms.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, yeah.
So he's saying, if God does one of these things,
things he does all of these things.
Yeah, and he already said all things work for good for those who are called, which is one of those things according to his purpose.
So if you've received the gospel, right, then you can count on God to do all of the other things he's promised to do.
And he's going to say in the rest of chapter 8 that we didn't read, we're not reading everything.
We're going to read enough trust me but we're not really he's going to say this is where he talks about nothing be able to step
from the love of God, right, from God's side.
And so he makes this, this huge argument that
from God's side, God keeps his promises to us.
You do not have to worry about God not following through on his promises.
Right, the promises he's made.
Okay. But then as we get to the end of chapter 8,
there is at this time, for St. Paul,
a big objection
someone might offer. Well, wait a minute. Didn't God make all those promises to Abraham?
Right. Didn't he make all those promises to Israel? And a lot of the descendants of Abraham
ate doing so good. Right. Right. And a lot of the the the Israelites they do it so hot. Right?
10 drives of him or god
right and St Paul you're coming here to us telling us Jesus is the Messiah and
looks like most of the Jewish people disagree with you.
Deboot right so what's going on with that and so as we get into what's now
chapter nine remember these chapter divisions are
original but as we get into what's now chapter nine what St Paul's doing here
beginning in Chapter 9.
is he's answering that objection.
Yeah, so but before we dive into chapter nine,
we do now actually have some people calling.
Oh, yeah, it was, I don't know, it was blank for a while and suddenly boom, boom, boom,
and I'm getting all these people in the chat saying I'm trying to call.
It was destiny to happen.
But yes, so our first caller tonight is a Rossine.
I hope I'm pronouncing that correctly.
So Rossine, are you there?
Yes.
Hello, father.
Hello.
Hello, and my understanding is that you are 11 years old, is that right?
Yes, and father Tim Curran's daughter.
Oh, wow. Hello, father Tim. I'm sure you're listening in with your daughter.
That is a lovely Irish name you have there, Ocene. So what is what is your question, your comment for us tonight?
I have a question on how people elect, elect, say, when people elect, say,
When people decide to glorify people as saints, does God automatically have to agree with them?
That's a good question. So here's how I would explain it.
It is God who makes people saints, right, with their cooperation with him.
So if they're faithful to him and especially if it's in a really big
big way. That's how we usually recognize as someone's
the same. They're really truly faithful to God in a big way.
And God then works with them to make them holy, right? To make
them like himself, to make them as Christ says equal to the angels.
And so then after their after their death, then the church will
sometimes, if God permits it, recognize that this is what
this happened. Right? And so then that
In addition, comes to a lot of different means.
The biggest one is looking at their life and seeing that their life really has this major
manifestation of the holiness of God.
And so then often there will be some kind of informal veneration of a person that happens,
But ultimately it takes a group of bishops in Synod to make the decision to officially
or glorify someone as a saint.
And it's a long process, and sometimes when they're going through the process,
they discover, hey, this isn't a good idea, we're just gonna not do it.
There have been people that they've been investigated for canonization and that gets set aside,
because they discovered it wasn't a good idea, or there wasn't enough evidence of holiness, or whatever.
Right.
And I will tell you.
you. You may not know this, Rossine, but there have been some cases of some accidental canonizations.
For instance, there were, I actually only just learned this recently, there were some cases in which
names of people were canonized in the Russian Orthodox Church because there was, you know,
testimony about them being treated badly by the Soviets or something like that. And then it was
later discovered that those
people were still alive and they just sort of quietly dropped their names off the list.
You know, so it is possible that mistakes can be made, but over time, the stuff gets sifted out.
So it's not like the bishops make a choice, you know, to can and I, someone is saying,
then God has to say, okay, I confirm or I don't, you know, it's really that God is the one doing
the work with the person, the actual real change in their
life and then the church recognizes that as being the case.
Human beings, including bishops, are not perfect and so that means it is possible that they
can make a mistake.
And as I said, there are sometimes mistakes that have been made, but over time, what happens
is that any mistakes get sifted out.
You know, does that make sense?
Yes, thank you very much.
You're welcome.
Thank you so much for calling.
Nice to talk to you.
Thank you.
I'm gonna take a couple more to
care of that one.
I mean, she you can be scared.
She seemed domesticated, so she
but it's those wild kids run
around the street.
You got to really look out for.
Yeah, she seemed she seemed
pretty.
Yes, yes.
From a good.
Yeah.
Okay, yes, we have William calling.
So William walked with Laura
the Spirit's podcast.
Hello, thank you. Can you hear me? We hear you. So what's on your mind, William?
Unfortunately, nothing quite so adorable as the previous caller. I come instead with
a question inspired by a friend of the show who is not Bartirman. So talking about the election in the case
of Israel.
and the churches were heading towards it, it seems.
And the first half of this show we discussed how the nation of Israel is not one of the 70 nations,
but it is still a nation, a 71st nation that was called by taking people from the other nations
and graphing them into the branch of Abraham.
But the church bike contrast, as I understand it, is super-nath-mational in that it is...
is not above the nation, I'm sorry,
it is above the nations without superseating them.
And its existence does not dissolve the component nations.
So if I'm following correctly,
God chose from the Tree of Abraham
and grafted some from other nations to build
as psionic Israel,
and then chose from the Tree of Abraham
and the nations to build the Pentecostal
super national Israel.
But also we say that the church is
Thank you.
real and the thigh in that thigh,
thigh naïc chosen nation and the
pentacostal chosen super nation
seem to be different from each
other. So what's going on there?
Hmm. I have thoughts, but I'm
going to just hand it to you
father because I know you have
very clear and precise ways of
talking about this particular
question. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So we've got to distinguish
something.
right? So the word that gets translated and we're as we keep going in Romans, we're going to get into some more of this. So this will be important to keep in mind.
The term that's translated Jew or Jews in most English translation of the Bible is actually Judeans,
which is essentially due to it, meaning descendants of the nation.
of Judah. Israel can refer to the northern kingdom of Israel, but generally
doesn't. Even though historically that kingdom was known sort of in some places
as Israel for part of its existence, that is referred to generally as Ephraim or
Joseph in the Hebrew Bible.
the northern kingdom. And the southern kingdom, even though it includes Judah and Benjamin and some of the leafites,
is referred to as just Judah.
And then Israel is the overarching term that includes both of those.
Right.
So,
the view that St. Paul is going to take and we're about to go through that.
passages where he's actually doing this. The same policy I'm going to take is that Israel has a lot of open space because Israel has a whole bunch of branches that have been cut off.
10 tribesworth, right? Plus not all of Judah, Judea.
Right?
Have been cut off or were in danger at the time he's writing of being cut off.
But you know anything about grafting, when you make a cutting, you can then graft in
a branch from another tree or another plant in at the point of the cut.
And so, for St. Paul...
people of the nations get grafted into that tree meaning they draw their life
from the root of that tree. That's what it means to be grafted in. And they can
now be called one people in one tree that one people is named Israel still.
But the branches, right?
You take a branch from one tree and graft it into another tree.
The branch doesn't change and become whatever that tree is.
So if that's a fruit-bearing branch, the fruit that it bears could be in an actual tree,
could be a different fruit than what the rest of the tree is bearing.
It remains a branch of the tree it came from.
But the branch draws its life from the root, the same root as the rest of the tree.
But it remains whatever it was.
And so for St. Paul, Israel is now constituted, post-second Pentecost, of the remnant of Judah,
The remnant of Judah with people from the nations grafted in who nonetheless remain members
of those nations.
So they remain Greeks.
They remain Syrians, Egyptians, right, whatever else they were, right.
But they are now part of Israel.
And the people of those nations are
are essentially for St. Paul replacing those tribes who are gone.
And he's going to say that more or less explicitly at the end of what we're going to read in this half,
even though a lot of people miss it when they read it.
Because they don't know their old testament well enough.
Does that make sense William?
I think so.
So from following that means that for St. Paul, the Torah is a component of
uh being
member of Joseph or Judah, but not being a member of Israel, is that true?
Yes, in the sense that there are people who have been grafted into Israel who, yes,
who the Torah is not directed to them. Yes. Okay, that makes sense. Thank you.
All right, thanks very much. We're going to take one more call and then we're going to move on
as we roll through parts of Romans. So Candace, welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast.
Hey, how are you guys?
Good, how are you?
I'm doing good.
long-time listener. I really mean this when I say it, y'all changed my life. I'm coming from a
Reformed Presbyterian worldview and I'm no longer in that world. But to explain, I still have a
really hard time understanding Romans 9. So my question is-
That's where we're going next.
Yes, I understand the concept of
like a more broad view of election that is not actually individualistic. But Esau and Jacob
are and Pharaoh in that passage are literal individuals. So how do we understand election
in that passage where it's actually speaking of individual? Oh man, so we just say just keep listening.
Well, I'll give you a general thing and then we're going to get into the nitty gritty of it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
as we go through it. So the general, the general thing is, right, the general thing is,
St. Paul here is very specifically talking about the promises to Abraham.
Right. The promises made to Abraham.
And there's two parts to those promises.
One of those parts is salvation, right? It is theosis. It is becoming like the stars of heaven, right?
But then the other piece is the land and
Them being given the land at the end of Joshua
Right as Joshua says they were given all the land they were promised at the end of Joshua
Sorry, dispensationalists see where equal opportunity
And that land was the symbol then of the bigger promise.
And so what St. Paul is going to do in the case of Jacob and Esau is he's going back to
Jacob and Esau and he is going to talk about their relationship with those land promises.
Scrape it.
use the relationship of Jacob and Esau's receiving the land promises to talk about then the receiving of the bigger promises.
So St. Paul is in no way saying that Esau went to hell.
So we didn't really hate him.
Well, we're going to talk about what that means.
Yeah. Right.
It's exactly what we're going to talk about what that means.
Right?
Okay.
But we'll get to...
But key to this, key to this, key to everything we're going to do is we're going through these texts.
Is that St. Paul is a person who had literally memorized the Torah in Hebrew.
Who was intimately acquainted with it, and he's writing to and arguing with and discussing with other people who are deeply
deeply, innimately acquainted with the Torah.
So when here a...
refers to Esau. These are people who know the whole story of Esau, right, from Genesis.
It all its detail, right? And most, I dare say most readers of Romans today are not as
is ultimately equated, right?
If you just read Genesis, there's nothing
in there that would imply to you.
that Esau was a bad person, that he didn't worship God.
In fact, he looks much more pious
for giving and loving than his brother.
Right?
So if St. Paul is all of a sudden coming out of the blue
with, oh, by the way, this guy went to hell.
Right?
That's not a very good argument.
Like if I was trying to prove election to you, right?
And I said, well, listen, right?
I'll show you, right?
I'll prove to you that election is real, right?
Like, look at, look at, I don't want to choose to,
too many controversial examples just gave me to my brain.
All at once.
But anyway, they said, okay, look at Richard Nixon.
He died, went to heaven.
was elect. God loved him. James Earl Jones died in what straight to hell because God hated him.
Now if I make that argument to you, what's it gonna be your response to me? How do you know?
Yeah, how do you know? Right? Like, wait, what?
Right? Yes. And so there's nothing in Genesis. This is anything about
So
I think I'm going to heaven and Esau going to hell, right?
Yes.
There's nothing in there, the two reconcile at the end.
And it's Esau who motivates the reconciliation.
Yeah, he's kind of the bigger person.
He's the good guy in the story, right?
So St. Paul is just coming in randomly saying, like, oh yeah,
that's not a good argument for that position,
if that's really his position.
right? So you get the the Calvinist reading of this requires a sort of circular argument
right where you say well wait a minute right St. Paul says points out to show election that Jacob
was elect and Esau was reprobate and I say well how do you know
Jacob was elected Esau was reprobate they say well St. Paul says in Romans 9 that Jacob was elected Esau was reprobate
I'm like
That's just a circle, right?
You're just saying he's saying that because he says that, right?
Like, that's not...
Yeah.
That's not an interpretation.
Okay, but we're gonna go through now and we'll do,
hopefully, to show you a better way to read that,
that makes more sense.
Okay, awesome.
In the context of everything.
Stay tuned.
All right, awesome.
All right, thank you guys.
Thanks for calling Candace.
Although I do have my suspicions about James Earl Jones,
for reasons that you know and won't be clear to the audience.
I know.
It's a great story if you ever tell it.
to the world. I was shocked. I was like, uh, justified. Yeah.
Blood feud justified. Um, okay. Roman.
What was not.
Roman forever. St Paul now is entering his answering this
objection. You've just argued to us that the promises of God
don't fail. But when we read the Hebrew Bible and the Old
Testament, it sure looks like most of the descendants of Abraham,
Most of the Israelites
end up receiving those promises. What's up with that? Right, right, right. Okay, so all right,
Romans chapter nine starting with verse one, I am speaking the truth in Christ. I'm not lying. My
conscience bears me witness in the Holy Spirit that I have great sorrow and unceasing anguish in my
heart. For I could wish that I myself were accursed and cut off from Christ for the sake of my
brothers, my kids have been according to the flesh. They are Israelites and to them,
I'm belonging a dot-
the glory, the covenants, the giving of the law, the worship and the promises to them
belong the patriarchs and from their race according to the flesh is the Christ who is
God overall blessed forever, amen.
Okay.
Wait a second.
I was going to say, wait a second.
I thought the idea that Christ as God was invented in the fourth century.
Yes.
Clearly.
Well, he's God relatively, you see.
Oh, yeah.
Overall.
Oh, we're all...
Oh, you know, anyway, sorry, sorry, that's not what this episode is about.
I just had to point that out. Everybody. Yeah.
All certainly things he's got. Right.
So say Paul begins his argument by saying, you know, yeah, that's a good point.
Right. And as a Jewish person, he finds that deeply upsetting.
Right. And he has this great display of love that he would be willing to be
cursed and cut off from Christ, right? He would be willing.
He's saying he'd be willing to be damned. Right in order for
His the rest of the Jewish people to find salvation. Yeah, right
And in saying that he's kind of deliberately paralleling Moses
at the end of Exodus when
God is is ready to
Wipe out the Israelites and start over with Moses
it's like we'll just do the Abraham thing but we'll just start again with
you. I'm done with these people. And Moses not only
intercedes for them, but he asks God to blot him out of the book of life.
Instead of the Israelites, right? And this sort of monumental display of love by
Moses. I mean, these are the people who have been persecuting Moses too, threatening to kill him.
Right. And he's he's willing to do that for them. I will note for all you fans of
Pedal substitution area tonement out there.
that God then explains to Moses that that's not how he works.
That he does not punish the innocent for the sins of the guilty.
He would not, anyway.
Oh, sorry, PSA.
You're just like kicking the Reformation right in the gut tonight.
Right.
Like God literally says it doesn't work that way.
I will not do that.
Anyway.
But he didn't be able to save later. I'll do that
He didn't say, okay, Moses, but you're not the right guy.
He said, I don't do that.
Okay.
Man, getting right in the soteriology.
That's...
But so St. Paul reflects that same kind of love here.
Yeah.
Right?
And he says, he points out, right?
As he said earlier, back in, in beginning of chapter three, he says, the calling of God
is irrevocable.
Yeah.
Right?
Right? So...
The Jewish people for St. Paul are still called upon
to be a light to the nations.
They're still called upon, right?
For St. Paul, though, that involves them accepting Jesus
as the Messiah.
Hmm.
Right?
That's part and parcel of how they will fulfill that calling.
And he says, you're right.
They were given all these things, right?
All those things that he lists.
Right?
All of them.
They have all of this.
Right?
And those of you who are Gentiles who now haven't have received it from them.
Right? The way you worship the Messiah's from the Jews, right? On and on and on. This is all from them
that you've received. And so yes, it is this horrible thing.
Right? This horrible thing that so many of them
have not received and are in danger now of not receiving those promises.
Yeah, okay.
Alright.
but now, but it is not as though the word of God has failed. For not all who are descended from
Israel belong to Israel and not all are children of Abraham because they're his offspring, but
through Isaac, shall your offspring be named. Let's pause there. Yeah. Okay. What a good
one more verse to it. Okay. This means that it is not the children of the flesh who are the children
of God, but the children of the promise are counted as
offspring. Right. Okay. So it's a boy here Abraham had lots of sons. Not just Isaac
and his family either. He's saying that's how the song goes right. Father Abraham.
Batman. Son's. You just think that when you're in Sunday school back in the day. I
think at some point. I know. I'm one of them. So are you? Yeah. No, that's not what this
is referring to. This is referring to literal. He had literal sons. Yes. Lots of sons.
Yeah, Paul is starting with the literal.
Right. He starts with the literal meaning of what's in the Torah, right?
And then he's gonna go for that, but he says, look, literally, what's in there is he's got all these
sons, right? But they aren't all recipients of the promise in the same way.
Right. The line of promise, the line that's gonna lead to the Messiah,
that goes through Isaac. Right. Right. So he's making an argument, this argument is kind of the same
argument he makes in Goliath.
When he talks about how in those promises, the references to Abraham's seed, because
seed, Zara in Hebrew is a collective noun.
Yeah, but it could be singular or plural, depending on context.
Yeah, and in Greek it's explicit whether it's singular plural in the Spirama or Spiramata.
Right.
But in Hebrew it could be either like fish or deer in English, right?
and so
So, St Paul is saying, there are senses in which it is plural, and there's another sense
in which it is singular.
Right?
And so, he's making that same kind of argument here.
There's this sense in which it is singular.
It's going through Isaac.
Right?
So, he's beginning to construct an argument of, well, hey, you know, the way you observe this
thing working now with the promises of God is kind of the way it's always worked.
It's kind of the way
it's always worked. Continuing with verse 9.
Okay, verse 9. For this is what the promise said about this time next year,
I will return and Sarah shall have a son. And not only so, but also, when Rebecca
had conceived children by one man, our forefather Isaac, though they were not yet
born and had done nothing either good or bad, in order that God's purpose of
election might continue not because of works, but because of him who calls.
She was told the older will serve the younger, as it is written.
Jacob I loved but Esau I hated
Yes, okay
so
Abraham has a bunch of sons but the promises are reckoned through Isaac
Okay, okay, Isaac and Rebecca then have two sons. You've got Jacob and Esau right and
before
They're born
Right, before they've done anything.
God says the older will serve the younger.
Okay.
Esau will serve Jacob.
Right.
He will serve Jacob.
He will serve Israel.
Right.
So if you read then the rest of the Torah, you see that this is what happens.
or is the Torah the rest of the
revival. This is literally what happens. We are told in Deuteronomy chapter 2 that God brought
Esau's descendants to the land of Edom, which is part of the land, which was promised to Abraham.
Esau's grandfather, that God brought them into that land and gave it to them and drove out a bunch
of giant clans before them.
The same way he was going to do with Israel in the book of Joshua.
He did it with Adam first.
Okay.
And because of that, Israel was not to take a single foot of land.
It literally says a foot. It says the length of a foot in the text.
Israel was not to take a foot of land from the Edomites.
They're cousins, right?
Because that land, that piece of Abraham's inheritance,
and inside we give into the
It's the Edomites.
Yeah.
But then once Israel comes into the land, what happens?
Edom became a vassal country throughout most of the Old
Testament history, a vassal country to Israel,
later to Judah, meaning literally the older served the
younger.
And as long as that vassal relationship,
that covenant relationship.
between the nation of Judah and the nation of Edom pertained, Edom kept that land.
They received their share in the promises of God as long as they maintained that relationship
with Israel, with Judah who was the firstborn son, right? Remember, the Torah, it's the first
born son who inherits everything and then distributes the inherit-
with his brothers. Yeah. Remember Jacob got the birthright, the first born status,
well, Risa. Okay. But then what happens later? Well, we get this second quotation, Jacob,
I have loved, you saw, I have hated that quote, right, is from the time of the exile.
Yes, as it is written written there. Right. That is a quote from the time of the exile.
It is
not a quote from before Jacob and Esau were born.
Genesis does not say
that God loved Jacob and hated Esau.
This is said at the time of the exile
because Edom had turned on and betrayed and attacked Judah.
While Judah was going into exile.
Yes, so these are about nations now
or tribes or however you wanna conceive of it,
people groups.
Jane can be easy.
as individuals are long, long dead. Right. Because of that betrayal, because they didn't keep faith,
because of their faithlessness toward their brother, Judah, the eunomites lost that land.
They lost their share in the promises. Okay. So knowing where this argument is going,
knowing the argument that Saint Paul makes this argument in Galatians, where is he going?
The ultimate first born, when we call it the first born of all creation and collotions,
and herons everything, and herons all the promises of Abraham according to Galatians,
as Abraham sees, is Christ. So if anyone, if anyone, if any descendant of Abraham
wants to receive a share of the promises from the first born, what do they have to do?
They have to remain faithful.
to their covenant relationship with the firstborn, with the Messiah, with Christ.
Right? So the itemites are no different for St. Paul than a faithless Jewish person.
It's faithfulness to the first born that keeps...
you a share. Remember first born among many brothers with whom he would share the inheritance,
but you have to remain in fellowship with him. Also, I would point out, and I say this only
because I have seen prominent Calvinists bang up and down on this Jacob I have loved
you saw I have hated.
Right?
And they specifically bang up and down on the hated part.
right? It says hated. Uh hated doesn't mean loved less, right? The word hated
there, the word me say in in Greek means hated, right? So it's saying God hated
he saw it doesn't mean loved less. It only means hate. If you're one of those
Calvinist. Allow me to direct you to Luke 14
verse 26, where Christ uses the same word, the same verb when he says,
if anyone comes to me and does not hate his father and mother, what?
He is not worthy of me.
Yeah.
Like you have to have rage against your mom and dad.
That only means hate.
Yeah.
Or wants us to hate our parents.
No, it's like turn away from or...
Yeah.
Well, and it could just mean love less.
Right. Right. Right.
Which is clearly what Christ means by it.
Yeah. You need to love your father and your mother.
Right. I know your father and your mother, but hate your father and mother.
But you can't love your father and your mother more than Christ.
Right. That's exact. Yeah. Right.
So anyway, that's just a side note.
If you're a Calvinist, even if you don't agree with me, even if you-
you come out of here and all this and you're still a die hard Calvinist, stop making that dumb argument.
About the verb to hate, okay, because there are other people who will pull out that verse from Luke on
you. Right. If it hasn't happened already. All right, verse 14. All right, verse 14. What shall we say
then? Is there injustice on God's part by no means? He says to Moses, I will have mercy on whom I
I have Mercy and I will have Compassion on whom I have...
passion, so that it depends not on human will or exertion, but on God who has mercy.
For the Scripture says to Pharaoh, for this very purpose I have raised you up that I
might show my power in you and that my name might be proclaimed in all the earth.
So then he has mercy on whomever he wills and he hardens whomever he wills.
Okay.
So again, Pharaoh not a good guy.
Very bad guy.
We still aren't technically told in Exodus.
I mean, he very clearly is a standard for the devil, but we're not actually told he goes to hell.
Yeah, right? His sort of eternal salvation is not in view, right?
But notice what the scripture St. Paul quotes says about Pharaoh.
For this very purpose, I have raised you up.
So you can show us power in him and that his name would be proclaimed in all the earth.
Okay? That's God saying, I have this purpose for you. Right? I have this purpose for you.
This is why I made you the Pharaoh. Right? This is why I made you the Pharaoh, the absolute ruler of the most powerful nation on earth.
Sir, I put you there
so that my name would be proclaimed to all the nations. Right? And this goal is accomplished.
Right? Because again and again, if you read Exodus, closely what you see God saying again
and again with the plagues. And when we were talking about heartening Pharaoh, it's heartening
Pharaoh so that the plagues can continue.
There's actually only one instance where God hardens Pharaoh's heart the other time Pharaoh does it but all the other times Pharaoh does it but the one time God does it it's so that this cycle of the plagues can be completed and all through the plagues it says over and over again.
That God is doing these plagues.
to reveal who he is to Israel, to reveal who he is to the Egyptians,
to turn from their idolatry.
Then they will know that I'm Yahweh, He says.
to reveal who he is to Pharaoh and to reveal himself by what he's doing in Egypt to all the other nations of the world who will hear about it.
Which is pretty merciful and compassionate to everybody involved.
God doesn't say he's judging Pharaoh and condemning Pharaoh. He doesn't say he's judging and condemning the Egyptian people.
people. God says he is judging and condemning on the night of Passover.
the gods of Egypt, the spirits, the demons, we'll control them.
St. Paul has read this very closely, right?
Now, Pharaoh, what happens?
What does Pharaoh's purpose end up being?
It ends up being this object lesson for the whole world.
It ends up being this cautionary tale for the whole world.
of what happens when someone thinks they're a god
and tries to stand up to the true God, right?
Even if he's the absolute ruler of the most powerful nation on earth.
This is what happens.
He becomes this cautionary tale, right?
What happened to Israel?
Again, St. Paul has read the prophets really carefully.
What are the prophets keep telling Israel as we're approaching the destruction of
the northern kingdom and the exile of the southern kingdom of Judah?
God keeps saying to them through the prophets,
I created you and called you to this purpose of being a light to the nations.
That through you I would reveal myself to the nations, my holiness, my purity.
You haven't wanted to do that.
So what does he say?
I'm going to make you an example to the nations of what happens, right?
When someone
is faithfulist to the calling I've given them. I'm going to make them an object lesson.
I'm going to make them a cautionary tale. Yeah, I mean, it just works the same way. So
St. Paul is using Pharaoh here, right? Because keep in mind, right? Who's he arguing with?
Right? He's arguing with people who are going to say, well, St. Paul, you can't be right
about Jesus being the Messiah because the rest of the Jews would have all accepted him
if he was the...
Messiah. Right? If God keeps His promises, why hasn't He kept His promises to everybody?
Set it for Abraham. If Saint Paul comes and just starts attacking Israel and Israelites and
his fellow Jews, that's not going to go anywhere in terms of our augmentation. So what does he do?
So he says things about Edom.
Right?
Because any of them who have read the Old Testament, they don't...
about what happened with Edom, right? They go, yeah, yeah, that, that, that happened. Yeah.
But he's saying, Israel, or, uh, Judea, right, has become like Edom.
He doesn't start talking about Israel. He talks about Pharaoh because they're going to read
Exodus. They're like, yeah, Pharaoh. Pharaoh was used by God as this object lesson, the nation,
this cautionary tale.
It's supposed to say, yeah, and now Jardiya.
and the destroyed Northern Kingdom,
like Pharaoh, they've become this cautionary tale.
Right?
And the purposes of God, because they refused.
And in both cases, it's faithfulness
that brought this about.
So verse 19.
All right.
Continuing on through chapter nine of Romans,
you'll say to me then,
why does he still find fault?
for who can resist as well.
But who are you, O man, to answer back to God?
Will what is molded say to its molder?
Why have you made me like this?
As the potter know right over the clay to make out of the same lump, one vessel for honorable
use and another for dishonorable use?
What if God designed to show his wrath and to make known his power has endured with
much patience vessels of wrath prepared for destruction in order to make known the riches
of his glory for vessels of mercy, which he has prepared before hand for glory.
even us whom he has called, not from the Jews only,
but also from the Gentiles.
Okay, go ahead and stop there before we get to the modes.
Okay.
So, we've got the lumps for the two different kinds of vessels.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, I mean people read this and they say,
see this is God making, yeah.
You know, there are bad vessels and good vessels
and that's just the way that it is.
And you're just clay, who are you?
Right now.
So if you go to Jeremiah,
if you're familiar with the prophets,
So you gotta be really...
familiar with the Old Testament to understand what Paul's doing.
You go back and read the Old Testament prophets, especially Jeremiah uses this analogy of the
Potter and the Potter's vessels. Let's talk about nations, not talking about individuals.
Number one. Okay. Number two, this translated there is a vessel for dishonorable use. This is a
a direct reference. St. Paul is making to God saying it's usually translated
English Moab is my washpot. It literally means Moab is my toilet.
Right. So he created Israel for one purpose. He created Moab for a different purpose.
Right. But again, what is St. Paul arguing about?
Okay. What is St. Paul talking about? St. Paul is talking about all the
generations, all those thousands and thousands of people descended from Abraham whose ancestors were
part of the Exodus from Egypt who came and settled in the land, all those people from those northern
tribes, right? Who were therefore centuries, God brought them into the land, gave them all these
blessings, gave them all these things, and in the end what happened to them. They're gone. They're wiped
out.
Yeah, carried off. They're wiped out. Right. And what was the point of that? Did God not know?
Did God not write?
And St. Paul is saying, well, what if?
What if God knew full well with those people were like?
right? Do that they were gonna end up suffering his wrath.
Right? New that. Full well, but he decided to also bring them out of Egypt, to also give
them land, to also send rain and give them crops and do all these good things for them,
knowing full well that they would continue to be faithless and eventually he would cut
them off and they would serve as this object lesson to the rest of the world of the cost
faithfulness. That's the argument, say, Paul's make.
with that make God a bad person.
Quick the opposite, right?
God is giving all these blessings
to people who don't deserve it at all.
These be patient with them when they don't deserve it at all.
But then because he finally comes to the end of his patience,
oh now the sun, you're going to accuse him of injustice?
Yeah.
Yeah,
What was coming to them, you know, right? God waited a long time.
He had again, he's speaking collectively because we know,
see, Paul's going to quote it here coming up. Yeah.
We know that in the time of Elijah, there were thousands of people who had not
bowed the need of bail in the northern kingdom.
It's not every individual in the northern kingdom is a repurpate.
They're saying nothing about individuals in the North.
kingdom. Prophet Elijah was from the northern kingdom, right? But it's talking about the kingdom
as a whole, those people groups, those tribes, right? You're coming and saying, oh God didn't keep
his promises to them. And say Paul's saying, oh yeah, he did. He went above and beyond with them.
Yeah.
Before he ultimately used them for the use.
that he put them to. But until then he would give them all kinds of undeserved kindness.
Right? That's the argument, say, Paul's making. Okay. Now we get back to the Hosea.
All right. Rolling on. Verse 25, as indeed he says in Hosea, those who are not my people,
I will call my people and her who is not beloved, I will call beloved. And in the very place where
where it was said to them, you are not my people. There they will be
called sons of the living God.
And Isaiah cries out concerning Israel, though the number of the sons of Israel be as the
sand of the sea, only a remnant of them will be saved.
For the Lord will carry out his sentence upon the earth fully and without delay.
And as Isaiah predicted, if the Lord of hosts had not left us offspring, we would have been
like Sodom and become like Gomorrah.
What shall we say then?
The Gentiles who did not pursue righteousness have attained it.
that is righteousness that is faith.
faith, but that Israel who pursued a law that would lead to righteousness did not succeed in reaching
that law. Why? Because they did not pursue it by faith, but as if it were based on works.
They have stumbled over the stumbling stone as it is written, behold, I am laying in Zion a
stone of stumbling and a rock of offense, and whoever believes in him will not be put to shame.
Right. So most of that, I think, is kind of self-explanatory,
Until we get...
to the end, right? Because then we get this, oh, faith versus works thing. Yeah, faithfulness.
Right. Yeah. So first of all, notice, St. Paul does not hear, could test that the law, the Torah,
leads to righteousness.
Yeah.
He's acknowledging that
it does, right? But he's saying, so then why did we've got Gentiles, we've got people who,
we've got non-Jewish people, people from the nations who are receiving these promises, right?
And we've got these Jewish people who had the Torah that leads to righteousness, right?
Who haven't received those promises? How does that work, right?
And this is where he makes this contrast between pursuing it by faithfulness or pursuing it by works, specifically works at the Torah.
We'll get into that in a second.
But the key is, right, he says they have stumbled over the stumbling block, right, and then he has the quote.
Right. Who is the stumbling block?
It's Christ.
price. So the faithfulness he's talking about is faithfulness to the Messiah.
Right.
So the core of what he's saying here is they've rejected the Messiah.
Right?
They've rejected the Messiah.
And since they've rejected the Messiah and he's the first born, I think Jacob and
Esau think Isaac and his brothers, right?
They've cut themselves off from receiving their share of the promises because he's the
inherited the promises, right? But what is what they have done in rejecting them?
Messiah, right, rather than receiving and being faithful to the Messiah and his commandments,
they have sought it through the works of the Torah. Don't have super time to go into this right now.
You can read Matthew, Thomas's published dissertation, Paul, and the works of the law,
but the way everyone in the first three centuries of the church literally everyone reads
Safe.
I think Paul means by works of the Torah, works of the law, is Jewish, the commandments
that were specifically given to the Jewish people.
Thanks for your conversation, right?
And Koshir.
Where did we start in chapter 9?
We started in chapter 9 with not everyone who's descended from Abraham is really descended
from Abraham.
Right?
He's referring back to our UNC-made-back-in chapters.
3, 4, and 5 about Abraham, that is faithfulness, but not everyone descended for a ears descended from Abraham.
Right? But Isaac, right? And so everyone else
needs to be faithful to Isaac. So the particular works he's talking about, the particular commandment he's talking about is, well, I'm circumcised.
I eat the Passover. I do these things.
That makes me a child of Abraham.
That means I receive a share of the promises, right?
By myself, apart from the Messiah, right?
I am a separated inheritor.
Say Paul says it doesn't work that way, right?
Esau, it didn't work that way for Esau.
Esau couldn't just claim a share of the promises.
We're from Jacob because Jacob's the first morning in Herod's house.
everything. He saw what circumcised.
Right. He saw what circumcised that didn't get him a share. He had to be in this
relationship of faithfulness with his brother, who was the first born.
Right. Same thing with that. That's the point he's making. He's come back
around to his original point.
You have to be in this relationship of faithfulness.
with the Messiah. Okay, so now a piece of chapter 10, we're not doing all of chapter 10.
Yes. There's a bunch of things in there about the Gentile. We've talked about them in other
episodes, but yeah, this really part sort of pertains to this. Yes. Okay. So chapter 10,
starting with verse five, from Moses writes about the righteousness that is based on the law,
that the person who does the commandments shall live by them. But the righteousness based on faith,
I'm say faithfulness. The righteousness based on faithfulness says, I'm reading from the E.S.
this video.
one, by the way. Do not say in your heart who will ascend into heaven, that is to bring
Christ down, or who will descend into the abyss, that is to bring Christ up from the dead.
But what does it say? The word is near you in your mouth and in your heart, that is the
word of faithfulness that we proclaim. Because if you confess with your mouth that Jesus
is Lord and believe in your heart that God raised him from the dead, you will be saved.
with the heart one believes and is justified and with the
one confesses and is saved. For the scripture says,
Everyone who believes in him will not be put to shame.
For there is no distinction between Jew and Greek.
For the same Lord is Lord of all,
bestowing his riches on all who call on him.
For everyone who calls in the name of the Lord will be saved.
Okay, so in verses five and six,
or actually five,
5-3-8. Right?
Our our our 16th century German friend Martin Luther
Will croak from his grave that oh see look
Say Paul is contrasting Moses writes about this righteous. This is based on the law based on the Torah
That the person who does the commandments will live by them
But the righteous is based on faith says da da da da da da right
When Saint Paul says at verse 6, but the righteous is based on faith or...
faithfulness says, right? And then he quotes, he's quoting
Deuteronomy. He's literally quoting Moses. This is not a
contrast. Okay, that but that but the English translators
put there is confusing you. He says, Moses writes about the
righteousness that is based on the law that the person who
It doesn't create a slip.
It's still lived by them.
Right?
And the righteous is based on faith says because he's now going to quote Moses.
This is it's both Moses.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's Moses and Moses.
St. Paul is not contrasting Moses with Moses.
I assure you.
Be like Moses, not like Moses.
That would be pretty nutty thing to do as a Pharisee.
Yeah, that doesn't make any sense.
right? So person who does the commandments lives by them. Yes. Yes. This is true. Right?
And you know how I know for sure that that's true? Because like four days ago now, four, five days ago,
days ago. Sunday is that four days ago? Is that five days ago now? Anyway, times of
light circle.
I read Christ, say exactly that.
Do these things and you will live about commandments from the Torah.
Say Paul is not contradicting Christ, right?
And the righteousness that is based on faithfulness says,
Do not say in your heart who will ascend it
heaven or who will descend into the abyss. The work is near you in your mouth and in your heart.
Deuteronomy. Right? And if you read that section, you can do so. These things are not too hard for you.
The whole point of what's being said in Deuteronomy is that being faithful to the commandments of God
is not too hard for you. There's something you could do. I know, I know Martin Luther and
generations of Protestants since him.
have taken this and told you it means the exact opposite of what St. Paul is saying.
Literally the opposite.
They've said that he's contrasting Moses with Moses and that the second Moses,
he is reading to mean exactly the opposite of what it very clearly means a deuteronomy.
But that makes no sense. That is on the face wrong.
There is no rational way to argue that that's what St. Paul is doing.
There isn't.
And when St. Paul adds his interpretive comments, right, who will ascend to heaven that is to bring Christ down,
meaning we don't need someone to go up into heaven because Christ has come down from heaven to us.
You don't need someone to descend into the abyss, into the depths of the earth.
because Christ did descend into the depths of the earth when He died and He rose
again. The word is near you in your mouth and on your heart, the word of
faithfulness, the word of Christ, the gospel. We have it. And being faithful to it,
being obedient to it is not too hard for you. That's what St. Paul is saying.
Right?
Sovation is there, right? And again, they've translated this again, believe, believe,
believe, believe, it's be faithful. Yeah. It's be faithful. It's not just think something
is true, right?
All right, we ready for chapter 11.
I think so.
Okay.
Romans 11.
I ask then, has God rejected his people?
By no means.
For I myself am an Israelite, a descendant of Abraham, a member of the tribe of Benjamin.
God has not rejected his people whom he forenew.
Do not know what the Scripture says of Elijah, how he appeals to God against Israel.
Lord, they have killed your prophets.
They have demolished your altars.
And I alone am left.
They seek my life.
But what does God's reply to him?
I have kept for myself 7000
men who have not bowed the knee to bail. So to at the present time, there is a remnant chosen by
grace. But if it is by grace, it is no longer on the basis of works, otherwise grace would no longer
be grace. Okay. So what's he saying here? As I mentioned, he refers to this episode of the life of
of the prophet Elijah. So he's saying...
Right? Now look, it's not that all of the Jewish people have fallen away, right?
None of the Jewish people have accepted the Messiah, right? St. Paul's like, I mean, I'm an example.
But he goes on to say, look, just like in Elijah's day, meaning just again, just like it's always been.
There's a core part of his arguments at chapter 9. It's always been this way. It was this way all
through the Old Testament, all through the Hebrew Scriptures. It was this way, right? So it shouldn't
surprise you that it's this way now.
All through the Hebrew Scriptures, most of Israel was faithless and there was a faithful
remnant.
Right.
And notice that remnant says chosen by grace.
Chosen meaning they have this quality.
It was compassive, right?
They are chosen.
And that's by grace, by God's action.
God's action makes them that way.
Right.
not on the basis of civil
works of the Torah, right? Meaning it's not because, right? These, these are the Jewish
people who got circumcised to the other ones didn't, right? The dividing line, the dividing
line is the Messiah, it's Jesus. That's what God has done in Christ, right? Him being the
Messiah and being faithful to him. That's the dividing line within the Jewish people.
and within all of the nations.
Yeah.
Right.
Versailles.
Okay.
What then?
Israel failed to obtain what it was seeking.
The elect obtained it.
But the rest were hardened.
As it has written, God gave them a spirit of stupor, eyes that would not see in ears that
would not hear down to this very day.
And David says, let their table become a snare in a trap, a stumbling block, and a retribution
for them. Let there.
eyes be darkened so that they cannot see and bend their backs forever.
So I ask, did they stumble in order that they might fall by no means, rather through
their trespass, salvation has come to the Gentiles, so as to make Israel jealous.
Now if their trespass means riches for the world and if their failure means riches
for the Gentiles, how much more will their full inclusion mean?
Right, so.
So he's saying Israel didn't end up receiving the promises.
He says, well, yeah, those who are elect, those who have this quality, those who have been qualified,
they obtained it and the rest are hardened.
So the rest become what? The faithless become what? They become an object lesson.
Right?
They still continue to serve the purposes of God, but it's a different purpose.
Okay?
And what is that purpose for St. Paul?
Right?
St. Paul makes sure that purpose is not, they're reprobating, they're going to hell.
No, it's to bring the nations in.
Right.
It's so that, right?
The gospel goes out to the nations.
And then, when the nations come in, right?
when
the rest of the Judeans who haven't accepted the Messiah see the nations coming in to worship the true God giving up their idols
Right giving up their immorality
Coming to worship the true God
Say Paul says then they'll be provoked to Josie and then they will turn and accept the Messiah
Right, so that hardening like Pharaoh's hardening has nothing to do with salvation
That's catalogical salvation.
has everything to do with this purpose they're fulfilling.
And say policies this purpose they're fulfilling now is ultimately being part of their eventual
salvation. Verse 13. Okay. Now I am speaking to Gentiles because I mean that's how Romans is working.
He talks to Jews and Gentiles because yeah. So I was talking to the people who are from the nations.
Yeah, right right. I would just say to everybody you know see your lengthy commentary on the whole
book of Romans and the whole Council of the God podcast as to why that's important.
But now I'm speaking to you Gentiles.
Inasmuch as then I am as I am an apostle to the Gentiles, I magnify my ministry in order
somehow to make my fellow Jews jealous and thus save some of them.
For if their rejection means the reconciliation of the world, what will their acceptance
mean but life from the dead if the dough offered as fruits first fruits as holy so as the whole
up and if the root is
holy so are the branches. So notice what he says here, right? St. Paul has been called by Christ
to go and bring his message of salvation to all the nations so that they will turn from their
idolatry, turn from their wickedness, turn to the to come and worship the true God in Jesus the
Messiah, right? But St Paul is
saying that he doesn't see that as an end in itself. Right? He thinks that through doing that,
he's going to help save his fellow Jews, help them come and find salvation. Yeah, there's definitely
hope here for Judea. And if their rejection has meant that the gospel has gone out, salvation has
gone out to the whole world. He says that eventual acceptance, I mean, that'll bring about the
the resurrection. Now we're talking about...
the Messianic Age. We're talking about Christ's return. That's what St. Paul is saying.
Now he gives this analogy in starting in verse 17 that we referred to earlier.
Okay, but if some of the branches were broken off and you, although a wild olive
chute were grafted in among the others and now share in the nourishing root of the olive tree,
do not be arrogant toward the branches. If you are, remember, it is not you who support the
the root but the root that supports you.
Then you-
say branches were broken off so that I might be grafted in. That is true. They were broken off
because of their unbelief, their unfathomableness, but you stand fast through faithfulness. So do not
become proud, but fear. For if God did not spare the natural branches, neither will He spare you.
So much for perseverance of the saints. But continue. There you go. Note then the kindness and the
severity of God. Severity towards those who have fallen, but God's kindness to you.
provided you continue in his kindness,
otherwise you too will be cut off.
And even they, if they do not continue in their unbelief,
their unfaithfulness, will be grafted in.
For God has the power to graft them in again.
But if you were cut from what is by nature
a wild olive tree and grafted contrator nature
into a cultivated olive tree,
how much more will these the natural branches
be grafted back into their own olive tree?
Yeah, we already comment on that analogy a bit.
with the collar so we could keep going.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
Lest you be wise in your own side,
I do not want you to be unaware of this mystery, brothers.
A partial hardening has come upon Israel
until the fullness of the Gentiles has come in.
And in this way, all Israel will be saved
as it is written.
The deliverer will come from Zion.
He will banish ungodliness from Jacob
and this will be my covenant with them
when I take away their sins.
Okay, this is, this section here is very important.
So there's this reference that St. Paul makes until the fullness of the Gentiles has come
in.
Right.
But again, this partial hardening, meaning those who have rejected Jesus of Asiah, they've
been hardened, right.
But again, he's talking about, well, there'll be this time, right, where they'll be provoked
jealousy and come back right in the end that's part of what St. Paul's working for.
And that's going to come after the fullness of the Gentiles have come in.
Yeah, it's one to serve the fullness of the Gentiles have come in.
Then all Israel will be saved.
Yeah.
I mean, isn't this a reference to the testament of Jacob?
Yes.
Yeah.
This is a reference to Genesis chapter 48.
Well, this is the Gentiles.
Again, you got to be really familiar with the Torah to understand, say Paul.
Yeah, he's using phrases that if you
know the Torah super well. Like, oh, oh, oh, I caught that reference. Yeah. You know, um, so
America in Genesis 48 Joseph brings his two sons, Ephraim and Manasseh to Jacob, his father,
for him to bless his sons. And these are going to be the two half-tripes, right? And Ephraim is the
younger of the two.
Okay, but Ephraim is going to be the numerically largest and most powerful tribe of the northern kingdom. Yeah, and there are so much so that it's the Psalms.
Yes, so much so that the northern kingdom gets called Ephraim.
Right. In the Psalms and the prophets, it's referred to as Ephraim, like we said before.
There's Ephraim and there's Judah. Right. That's the way of referring to the two kingdoms.
And so as we see so many times in Genesis,
even though Ephraim is the younger,
Jacob crosses his...
left in right hand so he puts his right hand on Ephraim. He blesses him. Right. It gives him the
older brother blessing. Joseph tries to correct him and Jacob's like, no, no, the thing.
And what does he say to Ephraim? He says, your offspring will become the fullness of the Gentiles.
Yeah, which the fullness of the nations a reference to the northern kingdom
being carried off, being dissolved, and dissolved into the nations. Right. So the idea
then is that when the nations come to worship Israel's God, it's the return of Ephraim,
right? Effectively. Because the promise over and over again in the prophets is that all Israel will
be saved. Ephraim and Judah will be bound back together. All the tribes, all Israel will be saved.
Right, and so say Paul, let's say Paul see
and St. Paul isn't making this up. This is referred to go back to our episode on the testaments of the 12th Patriarchs. This is an idea in Second Temple Judaism
before St. Paul gets to it.
That through the dissolution of the Northern tribes into the nations, right, the nations would come back in and be grafted in to fill all those spots where those branches were cut off.
So the way all Israel is saved to the way the whole
12 tribes is saved is by the people of the nations coming in and taking taking the place
of those tribes. That's exactly what St. Paul is saying here and it's clear again if
you know the Torah that he's referring to. Yeah. All right. It's finished us out here.
Okay. And we'll finally finish the second half. Almost two hours in. Okay. Almost three
hours. We're going to be saved. We'll be saved. Yeah. Thank you very much for that. Okay.
records the
gospel, they are enemies for your sake. But as regards the election, they are
beloved for the sake of their forefathers. The they here, by the way, is
Israel, because he's talking to the Gentiles now, right? As regards
election, they are beloved for the sake of their forefathers. For the gifts and
the calling of God are irrevocable. For just as you were at one time disobedient
to God, but now have received mercy because of their disobedience. So they, too,
have now been disobedient in order that by the mercy shown to you, they
All right.
also may now receive mercy.
Kinda goes around, comes around.
For God has consigned all to disobedience
that He may have mercy on all.
O, the depth of the riches and wisdom and knowledge of God.
How unsurczable are His judgments
and how inscrutable His ways?
For who has known the mind of the Lord
or who has been His counselor
or who has given a gift to Him
that He might be repaid,
for from Him and through Him and to Him are all things.
to him be glory forever.
Amen.
You just want to end the second half there.
Do you have anything you want to say about that?
You want to step on St. Paul's climax there?
I guess.
I don't know.
I mean,
I'm going.
Yeah, but I love what he does here, right?
He's like saying, it's going back and forth.
Like he's like saying, okay,
so Israel is in this sorry state
so that you Gentiles could be brought in.
but
when Israel sees you being brought in,
they're gonna wanna get on board as well.
Right.
You know, so there's a lot of falls going on here,
but there's gonna be a lot of getting up as a result.
Yep.
All right.
Well, that wraps up the second half.
We have one more half to go
on this very special election episode
of the Laura Spirits podcast.
So we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment.
Thank you.
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF
Radio.
How do you explain the sacraments? It's easy to say they're mysteries that we have to
take on faith or on the authority of tradition, but that is not how the early Christians understood
them, to them and to all ancient people.
the idea that physical objects had spiritual power was very intuitive, whereas modern people
tend to find this difficult, bizarre, or even un-Christian.
This is because we live in an era shaped by secularism, a way of viewing a world that's
incompatible with sacramental thinking.
Because secular ideas are at the heart of our culture, modern people tend to think in
secular ways without realizing it, even the most well-meaning of us.
How then do we live in but not be of a secular culture?
understand the enchanted, sacramental way that the early Christians viewed the world.
But we also need to understand secularism.
What is it really?
Where did it come from?
And how does it influence how we think about religion?
Journey to reality, sacramental life in a secular age breaks down these important issues
in accessible, non-academic language and is an ideal introduction for young readers,
catechumans, and seekers, as well as for any Orthodox Christians who want to deepen their
understanding of the sacraments.
Journey to reality.
life.
in a secular age by Zachary Porcou.
Now available at store.angentfaith.com.
Again, that is store.angentfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
And so I know the voice of Steve just told you to call her.
everybody, but we're actually closed down the phone lines so because it has already been a nice beefy episode.
And we have to hour this. I know, I know. I know. It's true. What can I say? But you know, it all comes down to when this father and
and you get to go to sleep.
So you thought you were gonna find out the results
of the election and not have to stay up late?
Ha ha ha.
Ha.
I mean, I just keep hoping for 1984 all over again where it was like over at eight p.m.
I'm like, 99 states.
I know. I remember that. That was the first.
That was the first election that I remember staying up for.
Yeah.
You know,
I remember as a kid, as a little kid, just feeling really bad for Walter Mondale.
I know.
Like, oh,
That's like, I mean, you know, I was nine, but it was like, that's like getting, you know,
pick last for dodgeball 50 time with
49 times. 49 times. Yeah. Like, and Minnesota said, we want you, Walter Mondale. We want you.
He was the second best politician in the country at the time, you know, but no respect.
Yeah. Okay. Sorry, Calvinists. Yes. That's no connection to Walter Mondale, by the way.
We're not a flag.
Walter Mondale was a Calvinist.
I don't know what is the obvious or in some way like Walter Mondale or even there are
many Calvinists in Minnesota.
Yes.
Many have voted one was chosen.
I don't know, but yes, yes.
No, this is just the episode where we just have to say that it's required by in our
contact to say that at the beginning of each of each half.
So yes, we are being a little pugnacious.
Yes.
So how about hugely in Matthew 22 where it says many are called fewer chosen?
Yeah.
So we're going to be fortunately for Father Andrew, you know.
He went and got the early bird dinner at 3 p.m. at the local Bob Evans.
He's an elderly man now.
He needs a drink as high as I'm only going to sleep.
Slightly younger than you.
We're going to try and pull all this together.
You never sleep.
So yeah, so I wait.
Um, so, yeah.
So, um, yes.
Matthew 22 verse 4
14 says many are called, but fewer chosen.
Right?
And what's interesting, and the reason we're bringing this up here now in our third half,
is that if you go to go back to, and I know it's been a long time since we were at the
beginning of the second half, but Romans 830, we're talking about those whom he predestined,
he also called those whom he called, he also justified those whom he justified, he also
glorified. If you look...
Look at patristic commentary on Romans 8 verse 30.
The Church fathers aren't concerned about any golden chains of redemption or any of that
kind of stuff, or predestinarianism.
What they're concerned about is, wait, does it this contradict Matthew 20 verse 14 that
many are called but if you are chosen?
Yeah.
By the way, I just have to say, because I just had to look this up.
Walter Mondale was in fact a Presbyterian.
Wow.
So it all comes together.
Right.
Sorry Walter Mondale.
About 1984 and your Calvin.
It's probably PC USA, though.
I mean, yeah, probably out of the really Calvinists.
Are they really Calvinists?
At some point they might have been.
Not anymore.
That's for us.
We're actually he would have been he was probably most of his life.
He's probably united Presbyterian before the guy.
together. His dad was a Methodist minister apparently. Oh well then yeah definitely. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Definitely. Anyway. Okay. Sorry. Sorry. I know. I just had to look that up. Like what religion was Walter Mondo.
Yeah. What are his joining a Calvinist denomination after having a like Wesley and dad was like youthful rebellion.
In Minnesota.
Oh, son, I'll show you.
I'm gonna become president.
dang our minion. Anyway, okay. So, so yeah, the fathers were there really
roads 830, right? Because of course, as we said, they're reading it, you know,
frankly, the way we did at the beginning of chapter two, it's say, well, say Paul
saying if he does one of these things, he does all of these things, right? And this
says if he if he calls you, he does all these things. But Matthew 22 14 says, many
here called but if you are chosen that
makes it sound like you can be called
and by God it he doesn't do those other things, right?
Isn't that a contradiction?
But here's what they point out.
Matthew 22 verse 14, many are called, but if you were chosen,
is the end of a parable that Christ tells.
Yeah.
And the preceding verses of Matthew 22,
parable the wedding banquet with the guy who shows up
without a wedding garment.
Right.
Yep.
And so, right, many are called, meaning lots,
Lots of people were invited.
the wedding. This guy shows up without the garment. Right. He's not chosen. Yeah. The
parable doesn't go that the king who offers the banquet goes around all his wedding guests
and says, I choose you. I choose you. I choose you. I don't choose you guy without a wedding
garment. Yeah. No. He or show or even show me your invitation. Like some of you showed
up uninvited. Right. Right. No. I only chose to invite.
of you. Yeah. Yeah. It was a, you know, if there's choosing going on, it's the guy who showed up
without the garment who made that choice. Right. But he doesn't have this status of chosen.
And chosen here has to do with showing up in the wedding garment, meaning it's an issue of qualification.
Yeah. It's an issue of having qualified yourself. Right. Uh, in terms of that call. Right. So the
The call was what?
You are invited to a wedding feast.
What is the faithful way to answer that call?
To go and purchase a wedding garment, put it on and arrive in a timely manner to the wedding feast.
Yeah.
Right?
So he's faithless.
He doesn't do what he was supposed to do.
Right?
And so he doesn't receive the promise that lay behind that call.
So in Romans, say,
Paul is talking about, look, God is going to follow through.
God is going to be faithful.
The question is whether we're going to be faithful, right, to the call.
Not whether God's going to be faithful to His promises, right?
Another very important passage.
Second Peter 1 verses 5 through 11.
Okay.
distinct Calvinists.
For this very reason, make every effort to supplement your faith with virtue and
virtue with knowledge and knowledge with self-control and self-control with steadfastness and steadfastness with godliness and godliness with
brotherly affection and brotherly affection with love.
But if these qualities are yours and are increasing,
they keep you from being ineffective or unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.
For whoever lacks these qualities is so near-sided that-
is blind, having forgotten that he was cleansed from his former sins. Therefore, brothers, be
all the more diligent to confirm your calling and election, or as it says in the gold king James,
make your calling election sure. For if you practice these qualities, you will never fail.
For in this way, there will be richly provided for you an entrance into the eternal kingdom of
our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. Right. Yeah, it's so interesting that he says,
If you do this, that's gonna give you the entrance.
Yes.
This is not about what happens after you're in.
Yeah.
Yeah, this is about entering into the kingdom, right?
So if you wanna enter into the kingdom, right,
that's the promise, right?
You've been called to.
That's what you've been called to.
You've been called to the kingdom of God.
So in order to receive that promise,
You have to make your calling an election sure.
That means your election isn't sure.
Yeah. It isn't certain.
This is the Bible. That's what it says. Yeah, you got to work out your salvation with fear and
says it isn't sure. Okay. And this is not about, as I've heard certain Calvinists, and this is a
bad argument. So don't make this argument Calvinists, but I've heard some people say this.
This is not about making...
you sure about your salvation. Yeah, I just don't feel sure because it doesn't say that.
It doesn't. This is not psychology. This is this is not about psychology. This is making your
colleague in selection sure, right? Yeah. And how do you do that? Back to verse five, you make every effort.
That's working. That's doing things. You can't get around that. Make every
every effort to supplement your faithfulness with virtue and virtue without each of these
things because if you have those qualities which you you gain those qualities, those qualifications
that constitute your election and make it sure you gain those qualities through effort if
you have them through that effort and if they're increasing through that effort they keep
for being in effect floor unfruitful.
And therefore, you're calling in Alexi's made sure and you gain an entrance into the
kingdom of Lord Jesus Christ.
That's what St. Peter says there.
That's simply what it says.
Yep.
Now I know, right?
I know.
There are some, Calvinist folks out there who will come and say, that's a really hard
passage.
It's really unclear.
We need to interpret the unclear passages like this based on the clear passages.
And I'm going to say the clear passages like what?
Like Romans 9, we just went through that.
Romans 8, 10, 11.
Right?
The passages typically say are clear.
Don't clearly say what you need them to say.
And therefore, you can't sort of use them to try and jimmy and squelch what this one clearly says.
is this text?
is actually really clear. The difference between clear and difficult is not agrees with me versus
disagrees with me. Oh man. Right. So the issue here is about qualifying or not qualifying.
Through the acquisition of virtue, through the acquisition of the Holy Spirit, which is done
through faithfulness, which includes effort.
So, Israel historically, the story of the Hebrew Bible, the story of the Old Testament,
is Israel proved by and large, not everyone.
Right?
Now again, we're not talking about every individual, because there's this remnant, always,
in every generation, great saints of the Old Covenant.
But on the whole, the nation of Israel was unfaithful and failed to live up to its calling
to serve as the light to the nations.
But St. Paul says that calling remains because the calling is irrevocable.
So you heard at the end of Romans 11.
The nations have been called to worship the true God.
That's a calling that comes out of Israel.
Salvation is from the Jews, as Jesus says.
But now the church constituted primarily of Gentiles has an inverse calling to Israel's original calling.
We're now called to prove.
the Jewish people, the jealousy to get them to return to God's Messiah.
What does that mean? That means Jewish people should look at their Christian friends and neighbors.
See the holiness we practice, see the righteousness we practice.
So you've given up evil things, see how we follow the true God,
and that should inspire them to accept Jesus as their Messiah.
Allow me to say that collectively,
we're talking about everyone in history who has called themselves a Christian.
We haven't done that.
Yeah. Right?
You're average Jewish person.
If they go back through history and look at people who have called themselves Christians,
and the way they've acted, not just toward Jewish people, but it just in general.
Right?
would not be awestruck by our holiness and kindness and gentleness and love.
Okay.
Now, obviously we can only control ourselves and our own communities, right?
But this is, and beyond just the question of the Jewish people, I mean, that's the context
in which St. Paul's talking about it in Romans, right?
So that's why we refer to it here.
But in general, right, this is, I have people all the time who come and join the Orthodox
Church and they have family members, sometimes there's spouts, right?
older children of theirs, other family members.
Right? Who?
Sometimes they're antagonistic to the Orthodox Church. Sometimes they're just not interested. Sometimes they have qualms. Whatever their relationship is, they're not ready to join likewise. Right?
And when I tell all those people when they're joining the Orthodox Church is, all those other people in your life are gonna be looking at you.
And they're gonna see how you live and what you do. And if and how being part of the Orthodox Church changes your life.
What kind of
holiness, what kind of fruit it brings out in you. And if they see good fruit there, if they see
these good things happening for you, that will draw them into the church. Not you arguing with them,
not you sending the memes, right? Them seeing you, living a Christian life, right? So we're not
just talking about Jewish people. We're talking about everyone in the world, right? Should be able to
look at us in our lives the way we live them in as a person and collectively as a
the way we live as a church should be able to look at that and see Christ there and be drawn to it.
Right.
That's our calling.
It's kind of our calling as Israel.
And so for St. Paul, the way we find salvation, it's not just St. Paul.
This is all of the apostles, all of the New Testament writers.
Right, this is really very simple.
It's not really that hard.
Right? God has given us a calling. He's given us a general calling as Christians. Right?
There's a Christian way of life in community. Right? That we believe has been preserved
in the Orthodox Church. Right? If nowhere else, it has been preserved in the Orthodox Church.
We don't need to comment on where else somebody else might find it, but it's definitely here.
That way of life.
leads to salvation. We're called to live in that way. We find our salvation by
being faithful to it. But there's also another layer. There's a very personal
layer. It's not all collective. Yeah, right? So there's a way every Christian
should live. There are things, you know, love one another. There are commandments
that are to all of us, right? But there are also for St. Paul and for all the
other New Testament writers, particular gifts and particular callings that
God is given to you. Yes, they're
as your friend received both.
different people have different abilities, different gifts, different talents, you know, we're not all good at everything.
Yeah, and so we're called to fill different roles in our families, in our communities, in our parish communities, church communities.
Right, we're called to different roles based on having these different gifts. Right, and spiritual gifts are not about babbling incoherently
or uh...
jumping up and down or working miracles or predicting the future. Okay, spiritual gifts are
according to the Bible more about some people being able to paint icons, some people being able to
teach, some people being good at cleaning. Yeah, administration. Some people being good at sewing
things for the church. Some people being good at baking bread.
for the Eucharist. Some people, right, being good at preparing food for the community to eat and have
fellowship, right? All kinds of things, right? You know, I'm really blessed in my parish in that I
have a bunch of people who have trades who could do things like electric and plumbing and things,
right? That's a spiritual gift too. Right? That you can offer back to God,
Right?
Look at this.
spirit. And so we find salvation very simply by being faithful to those callings in our
life. And we risk salvation. We risk that when we're faithless to that calling, when
we abandon that calling that God has given us. It's really, it's really that simple.
Yeah.
So.
So I know some of you people in the YouTube chat were cheering for a four hour episode.
I don't know who knows.
Maybe Father Stephen will give us 45 minutes at the end.
I did used to preach in Protestant churches.
That's true.
I know.
I mean, the Germans I grew up with were 45 to 60 minutes, typically, and often went longer.
Yeah.
Okay.
Yes, this episode is a whole lot of sorry Calvinist.
but its purpose is not actually just an apologetic against Calvinism. Right? There is actual
positive content to what it means to be elect slash chosen. And I think that a lot of this gets
distorted, confused, misunderstood because of the particular current swirling around at the
the time of the referee.
which is when a lot of this stuff gets the articulation that most of us are now familiar with,
and maybe even this is the way we just tend to read the Bible because this is what we were trained in or whatever.
And I think one of the, I mean, it's well known, for instance, that a quick talk about the personality and experience and life story of people like Martin Luther and John Calvin,
and that's very interesting.
But I'm not going to sort of locate everything in that,
although I think that's an interesting trail
to walk down and look into it, you know?
But also, I mean, there's one of the things
going on around the Reformation
and a lot of people don't realize this,
is that there was a strong sense that,
amongst a lot of Christians in Western Europe,
that the end of the world was...
coming. And soon, right, there was a lot of
millenarianism. There was a sense that they were
really living in the end times. And, you know, thus, they were able to look at
Roman Catholic church and they would say, this is the final apostasy, the Pope is
the anti-Christ. And by that, they didn't just mean that all
popes are anti-Christ, but like they actually believed like he was the last
one. You know, this was it. And so as a result, then, for a lot of people, the
Reformation was a sense of this
final sort of push of the gospel, a final cleansing of Christianity before the return of Christ.
Okay. And therefore, if you have this sense of like imminent return, then the question of,
how do I know that I'm saved has a really heightened character to it?
You know, and if you do have a...
a neurotic personality, which I'm going to go ahead and say that Martin Luther seemed to have one.
Then you know, you might do things like go to confession multiple times a day and
agonize over whether you truly are saved, which he did, he did. But he's not the only one who, you know,
has those kinds of feelings. You know, with that sense that the world is ending and
than a lot of
very, very heightened emotional states can come around.
And then that has can have theological ramifications,
especially if you happen to have a bunch of political rulers
willing to give you space to explore other kinds of theology
than the ones that had been dominant for centuries
in your region, right?
So what does that have to do with us today?
Well, I mean, there are a lot of people that feel like
wherein the end times, right?
I mean, we did a hold.
series of episodes on eschatology, you know, if you haven't listened to them, well, spoiler alert,
we've been in the end times for two thousand years. So I'm not saying this isn't the end of the end.
I mean, who knows? I might not wake up tomorrow. It might be the end of the world. It might be just
the end of my world. I don't know. You know, eschatology is always, always nearby. We're always
participating in that in the end of the world in one way or another. But I
I think there is a sense that a lot of people have now that like, okay, this is really bad.
The way that the world is right now.
And honestly, even though we've made a number of political election jokes in the course of
this episode, sometimes the way that politics moves makes people feel like it's the end of
the world, or at least that it's going to be the end of their world.
I'm now
I mean, we both made reference to the 1984 presidential election.
That's the first election that I remember.
I was I was nine years old when that went down.
Father Stephen was was the same age as I am, but a couple months more.
And so I remember a lot of elections.
And especially I remember a number for a while.
There are people that that feel like, oh,
the Antichrist just got elected.
Literally, I recall for the last five or six presidential election.
people saying that, you know, this sense of the end of the world and one way or another
because they believe that whoever got just got elected is the worst possible person that could be elected, you know
and they're going to bring everything down, you know. And there are people who are even, I've even seen this again just in last week, people saying that they're going to kill themselves
because of the waiter.
and election turned out because of the sense of the world is ending.
My world is ending at the very least.
And my point in all this is not to make a comment about politics and the church by no means.
Although honestly, I think we need to hold all of these things going on in the world a lot more lightly.
That doesn't mean they're not serious.
They are serious.
But what's more serious is the big story.
And that's the story of Christ.
It's more serious.
Right? And so this question of how do I know that I am saved, this is a kind of a, it is
kind of a neurotic question. Right? I'm not saying it's bad to ask that question. But
it, especially if you keep returning to it and you obsess over it and you need to come
with a system for it, then it is kind of a neurotic thing to
to focus on, you know, to make the definition of your theology, for instance.
You know, it would be like a husband and wife where every day, you know, let's say I go to my wife
every day and say, no, I need you to tell me again that you're not going to divorce me. And how do I
know I'm not going to divorce you? I mean, what does that do to a marriage when that's what it's about?
It's not in good shape that relationship.
Right. So what does it come down to? It comes down to what St. Paul says it comes down to. It comes
down to faithfulness. Faithfulness, right? Not absolute mental certainty. Faithfulness, like this
This is my life, the life in Christ.
It is a way of acting, a way of being.
way of thinking, a way of loving, like all of these things, you know, it's an
in, it's ongoing because it's all of these very active verbs of things that you do.
And, you know, day one of when you've chosen to be faithful to Christ, you listen to the
call and you're trying to do the thing.
Day one, you know, you've just begun.
You've just begun.
And it's okay if you're worried.
It's okay if you're like, I don't know if I'm doing this right.
you
That's all right. It's okay. It's okay. You're going to fall down a gazillion times.
Just make sure you get up a gazillion and one. Okay. Just stay loyal. You know,
you know, it makes me think of the words of the great philosopher, you know, never going to give
you up, ever going to let you down. You know, the point is loyalty and faithfulness and
continue.
going on or not. And so, yeah, it doesn't need to be this neurotic thing. You don't need
to have some kind of signed contract. You don't need to, if you're just simply living this
life together, right? Like marriages can become very neurotic as a result of this. But friendships
tend to be less so. I'm not saying no friendships are neurotic, but people tend to expect less
from their friends than they do from their spouse. And so as a result, there's a lot more
breathing room. You know, a good marriage is one where there's plenty of breathing room and they
together. Right? And so, you know, we all want a lot of this language and scripture about
the, you know, Christ, the bridegroom, and we're the bride of Christ. And we want that kind of
intimacy in our spiritual life. And that's awesome and good. But you build that intimacy by this
mutual freedom and love for one another. Right? And so I think in many cases, we need to start with
thinking about what it means that Christ is also our friend.
And how do we be his friends?
And then that can develop over time.
So, yeah, that's what I have to say about that.
So, was that Rick Roll a reference to your C tier co-host?
It's true. He's a living Rick Roll.
All right, C tier co-host confirmed.
All right.
So, Lansman, your B tier.
It's great.
Anyway, wow, so
Wow gauntlet's thrown
so
Yeah, so
There's
There's a meme that's been going around for a long time. I don't know if I've seen it recently, but I'm sure it's still out there
That that orthodoxy is Christianity only harder. Oh, I hate that
I hate that I'm sorry I just had to jump into it. Well that's revenge
for that Aquinas thing earlier. So there is some truth to it in that, right? Of course,
Christ says, you know, broad as the way an easy is the path that leads to destruction, right?
Narrow is the way and straight is the path that leads to life, right?
But I think...
I think sometimes rather than taking that or hearing that or hearing that meme about orthodox
Christianity and being sort of challenged by it in a way that's sort of invigorating and
challenging and let's rise to the occasion, let's take our faith seriously.
Let's make every effort as St. Peter says, right?
Let's get down to business.
I think a lot of the time.
We just kind of go, man, this is hard.
This is too hard.
Right?
And we look at, we put in front of ourselves
as examples of faithfulness, you know,
even if we're like a married person.
So should you marry folks with kids?
And you put in front of yourself
as your image of the Christian you're supposed to be,
like a saint.
monastic who's living a different kind of life than yours who had a different calling
from God than you have. And we look at because we've chosen that particular model, we compare
ourselves to it and just constantly see our deficiency. Right.
I just constantly see how far away we are from where we should be.
When that shows us our sins, it's good, but what makes it good is not that we wallow
in our sins or feel guilty or feel bad.
Guilt is worthless, like most emotions.
I know I'm Jen Ex, but still.
The reason seeing our sins is good is that we can repent of them.
Look at that.
isolate them, we can go to war with them, we can do better. Again, we can be spurred on
to try and do better, to try to fix what we've broken, to try to be healed and to help
with the healing of others. So I want to come back to what St. Paul quoted, which is in
and in due to runny.
And in due to runny, it's talking about the whole Torah.
The whole Torah.
Off.
those commandments hundreds of commandments. God says what? Do not say who will go up into
heaven, who will go down to the piss. It's not far from you. It's in your mouth. It's
on your heart. It's not too hard for you. Right? God wants us to find salvation. He
He loves you, he wants you to find salvation.
He does not want you to perish.
He is not trying to make it difficult on you.
He is not trying to weed you out of the kingdom.
He's not trying to make sure you don't make it.
He wants you to make it.
Because he wants you to make it, because he loves you,
is giving you everything.
you need to work out your salvation. You have everything you need. We just need to start
exerting every effort. We just need to start working toward it. And the reason we're able
to do that, the reason we're able to go through whatever suffering and difficulty and hardship
we're going through and press on and keep making
that effort is that we know what St. Paul also told us that we read tonight.
Right? That regardless of that, God is going to be faithful. God is going to finish what
he started in us if we remain faithful. He is going to bring us home if we remain faithful.
We will continue to provide us with what we...
need. So any view of God or of holiness or of salvation, no matter how dressed up
in a classic with a giant prayer open is, that causes you to fall into despair is not
an image of God or an image of holiness, it's an image of the devil. Because it's an image
of condemnation directed toward you.
The image of...
discouragement directed toward you. Let's try and bring you down into
despondency. That's not from God. Not as with you. He's on your side. The Holy
Spirit is in your mouth and on your heart. It's written the commandments
there. So that if we're willing to follow him, we can keep them and we can find
That's what I have to say.
Amen.
That is our show for tonight.
Thank you for listening, everyone.
If you didn't get through to us live, we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordOfSpiritz at ancientfeet.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page.
You can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordOfSpiritz.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help to find a parish,
go to orthruxintro.org.
Join us for a live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
You could blow with this, you could blow with that.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page.
You can join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings
everywhere, but most importantly,
share this show with a friend who is going to love it.
Finally, be sure to go to www.exitpave.com.stokesupport
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasts
are stay on the air.
You could blow with this, you could blow with that.
Thank you, good night.
make that bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of Ancient
Faith Radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts,
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.